<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
          "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
  <properties>
    <title>
      Code of Conduct Policy
    </title>
  </properties>
  <body>
  <section name="Code of Conduct Policy">
<p>
We expect participants in discussions on the HBase project mailing lists, IRC channels, and JIRA issues to abide by the Apache Software Foundation's <a href="http://apache.org/foundation/policies/conduct.html">Code of Conduct</a>.
</p>
<p>
If you feel there had been a violation of this code, please point out your concerns publicly in a friendly and matter of fact manner. Nonverbal communication is prone to misinterpretation and misunderstanding. Everyone has bad days and sometimes says things they regret later. Someone else's communication style may clash with yours, but the difference can be amicably resolved. After pointing out your concerns please be generous upon receiving an apology.
</p>
<p>
Should there be repeated instances of code of conduct violations, or if there is an obvious and severe violation, the HBase PMC may become involved. When this happens the PMC will openly discuss the matter, most likely on the dev@hbase mailing list, and will consider taking the following actions, in order, if there is a continuing problem with an individual:
<ol>
<li>A friendly off-list warning;</li>
<li>A friendly public warning, if the communication at issue was on list, otherwise another off-list warning;</li>
<li>A three month suspension from the public mailing lists and possible operator action in the IRC channels.</li>
<li>A permanent ban from the public mailing lists, IRC channels, and project JIRA.</li>
</ol>
</p>
<p>
For flagrant violations requiring a firm response the PMC may opt to skip early steps. No action will be taken before public discussion leading to consensus or a successful majority vote. 
</p>
  </section>
  </body>
</document>
