<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<appendix
    xml:id="compression"
    version="5.0"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <!--/**
 * Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 * or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 * distributed with this work for additional information
 * regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 * to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 * "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 * with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 *
 *     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 *
 * Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 * distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 * WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 * See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 * limitations under the License.
 */
-->

    <title>Compression and Data Block Encoding In
          HBase<indexterm><primary>Compression</primary><secondary>Data Block
          Encoding</secondary><seealso>codecs</seealso></indexterm></title>
    <note>
      <para>Codecs mentioned in this section are for encoding and decoding data blocks or row keys.
       For information about replication codecs, see <xref
          linkend="cluster.replication.preserving.tags" />.</para>
    </note>
    <para>Some of the information in this section is pulled from a <link
        xlink:href="http://search-hadoop.com/m/lL12B1PFVhp1/v=threaded">discussion</link> on the
      HBase Development mailing list.</para>
    <para>HBase supports several different compression algorithms which can be enabled on a
      ColumnFamily. Data block encoding attempts to limit duplication of information in keys, taking
      advantage of some of the fundamental designs and patterns of HBase, such as sorted row keys
      and the schema of a given table. Compressors reduce the size of large, opaque byte arrays in
      cells, and can significantly reduce the storage space needed to store uncompressed
      data.</para>
    <para>Compressors and data block encoding can be used together on the same ColumnFamily.</para>
    
    <formalpara>
      <title>Changes Take Effect Upon Compaction</title>
      <para>If you change compression or encoding for a ColumnFamily, the changes take effect during
       compaction.</para>
    </formalpara>

    <para>Some codecs take advantage of capabilities built into Java, such as GZip compression.
      Others rely on native libraries. Native libraries may be available as part of Hadoop, such as
      LZ4. In this case, HBase only needs access to the appropriate shared library. Other codecs,
      such as Google Snappy, need to be installed first. Some codecs are licensed in ways that
      conflict with HBase's license and cannot be shipped as part of HBase.</para>

    <para>This section discusses common codecs that are used and tested with HBase. No matter what
      codec you use, be sure to test that it is installed correctly and is available on all nodes in
      your cluster. Extra operational steps may be necessary to be sure that codecs are available on
      newly-deployed nodes. You can use the <xref
        linkend="compression.test" /> utility to check that a given codec is correctly
      installed.</para>

    <para>To configure HBase to use a compressor, see <xref
        linkend="compressor.install" />. To enable a compressor for a ColumnFamily, see <xref
        linkend="changing.compression" />. To enable data block encoding for a ColumnFamily, see
      <xref linkend="data.block.encoding.enable" />.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>Block Compressors</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>none</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Snappy</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>LZO</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>LZ4</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GZ</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>


    <itemizedlist xml:id="data.block.encoding.types">
      <title>Data Block Encoding Types</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>Prefix - Often, keys are very similar. Specifically, keys often share a common prefix
          and only differ near the end. For instance, one key might be
            <literal>RowKey:Family:Qualifier0</literal> and the next key might be
            <literal>RowKey:Family:Qualifier1</literal>. In Prefix encoding, an extra column is
          added which holds the length of the prefix shared between the current key and the previous
          key. Assuming the first key here is totally different from the key before, its prefix
          length is 0. The second key's prefix length is <literal>23</literal>, since they have the
          first 23 characters in common.</para>
        <para>Obviously if the keys tend to have nothing in common, Prefix will not provide much
          benefit.</para>
        <para>The following image shows a hypothetical ColumnFamily with no data block encoding.</para>
        <figure>
          <title>ColumnFamily with No Encoding</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="data_block_no_encoding.png" width="800"/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption><para>A ColumnFamily with no encoding></para></caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>Here is the same data with prefix data encoding.</para>
        <figure>
          <title>ColumnFamily with Prefix Encoding</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="data_block_prefix_encoding.png" width="800"/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption><para>A ColumnFamily with prefix encoding</para></caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Diff - Diff encoding expands upon Prefix encoding. Instead of considering the key
          sequentially as a monolithic series of bytes, each key field is split so that each part of
          the key can be compressed more efficiently. Two new fields are added: timestamp and type.
          If the ColumnFamily is the same as the previous row, it is omitted from the current row.
          If the key length, value length or type are the same as the previous row, the field is
          omitted. In addition, for increased compression, the timestamp is stored as a Diff from
          the previous row's timestamp, rather than being stored in full. Given the two row keys in
          the Prefix example, and given an exact match on timestamp and the same type, neither the
          value length, or type needs to be stored for the second row, and the timestamp value for
          the second row is just 0, rather than a full timestamp.</para>
        <para>Diff encoding is disabled by default because writing and scanning are slower but more
          data is cached.</para>
        <para>This image shows the same ColumnFamily from the previous images, with Diff encoding.</para>
        <figure>
          <title>ColumnFamily with Diff Encoding</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="data_block_diff_encoding.png" width="800"/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption><para>A ColumnFamily with diff encoding</para></caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Fast Diff - Fast Diff works similar to Diff, but uses a faster implementation. It also
          adds another field which stores a single bit to track whether the data itself is the same
          as the previous row. If it is, the data is not stored again. Fast Diff is the recommended
          codec to use if you have long keys or many columns. The data format is nearly identical to
        Diff encoding, so there is not an image to illustrate it.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Prefix Tree encoding was introduced as an experimental feature in HBase 0.96. It
          provides similar memory savings to the Prefix, Diff, and Fast Diff encoder, but provides
          faster random access at a cost of slower encoding speed. Prefix Tree may be appropriate
          for applications that have high block cache hit ratios. It introduces new 'tree' fields
          for the row and column. The row tree field contains a list of offsets/references
          corresponding to the cells in that row. This allows for a good deal of compression. For
          more details about Prefix Tree encoding, see <link
            xlink:href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HBASE-4676">HBASE-4676</link>. It is
          difficult to graphically illustrate a prefix tree, so no image is included. See the
          Wikipedia article for <link
            xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trie">Trie</link> for more general information
          about this data structure.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section>
      <title>Which Compressor or Data Block Encoder To Use</title>
      <para>The compression or codec type to use depends on the characteristics of your data.
        Choosing the wrong type could cause your data to take more space rather than less, and can
        have performance implications. In general, you need to weigh your options between smaller
        size and faster compression/decompression. Following are some general guidelines, expanded from a discussion at <link xlink:href="http://search-hadoop.com/m/lL12B1PFVhp1">Documenting Guidance on compression and codecs</link>. </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If you have long keys (compared to the values) or many columns, use a prefix
            encoder. FAST_DIFF is recommended, as more testing is needed for Prefix Tree
            encoding.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>If the values are large (and not precompressed, such as images), use a data block
            compressor.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use GZIP for <firstterm>cold data</firstterm>, which is accessed infrequently. GZIP
            compression uses more CPU resources than Snappy or LZO, but provides a higher
            compression ratio.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use Snappy or LZO for <firstterm>hot data</firstterm>, which is accessed
            frequently. Snappy and LZO use fewer CPU resources than GZIP, but do not provide as high
          of a compression ratio.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>In most cases, enabling Snappy or LZO by default is a good choice, because they have
            a low performance overhead and provide space savings.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Before Snappy became available by Google in 2011, LZO was the default. Snappy has
            similar qualities as LZO but has been shown to perform better.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="hadoop.native.lib">
      <title>Making use of Hadoop Native Libraries in HBase</title>
      <para>The Hadoop shared library has a bunch of facility including
        compression libraries and fast crc'ing. To make this facility available
        to HBase, do the following. HBase/Hadoop will fall back to use
        alternatives if it cannot find the native library versions -- or
        fail outright if you asking for an explicit compressor and there is
      no alternative available.</para>
    <para>If you see the following in your HBase logs, you know that HBase was unable
      to locate the Hadoop native libraries:
      <programlisting>2014-08-07 09:26:20,139 WARN  [main] util.NativeCodeLoader: Unable to load native-hadoop library for your platform... using builtin-java classes where applicable</programlisting>
      If the libraries loaded successfully, the WARN message does not show.
    </para>
    <para>Lets presume your Hadoop shipped with a native library that
      suits the platform you are running HBase on.  To check if the Hadoop
      native library is available to HBase, run the following tool (available in 
      Hadoop 2.1 and greater):
      <programlisting>$ ./bin/hbase --config ~/conf_hbase org.apache.hadoop.util.NativeLibraryChecker
2014-08-26 13:15:38,717 WARN  [main] util.NativeCodeLoader: Unable to load native-hadoop library for your platform... using builtin-java classes where applicable
Native library checking:
hadoop: false
zlib:   false
snappy: false
lz4:    false
bzip2:  false
2014-08-26 13:15:38,863 INFO  [main] util.ExitUtil: Exiting with status 1</programlisting>
Above shows that the native hadoop library is not available in HBase context.
    </para>
    <para>To fix the above, either copy the Hadoop native libraries local or symlink to
      them if the Hadoop and HBase stalls are adjacent in the filesystem. 
      You could also point at their location by setting the <varname>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</varname> environment
      variable.</para>
    <para>Where the JVM looks to find native librarys is "system dependent"
      (See <classname>java.lang.System#loadLibrary(name)</classname>). On linux, by default,
      is going to look in <filename>lib/native/PLATFORM</filename> where <varname>PLATFORM</varname>
      is the label for the platform your HBase is installed on.
      On a local linux machine, it seems to be the concatenation of the java properties
      <varname>os.name</varname> and <varname>os.arch</varname> followed by whether 32 or 64 bit.
      HBase on startup prints out all of the java system properties so find the os.name and os.arch
      in the log. For example:
      <programlisting>....
      2014-08-06 15:27:22,853 INFO  [main] zookeeper.ZooKeeper: Client environment:os.name=Linux
      2014-08-06 15:27:22,853 INFO  [main] zookeeper.ZooKeeper: Client environment:os.arch=amd64
      ...
    </programlisting>
     So in this case, the PLATFORM string is <varname>Linux-amd64-64</varname>.
     Copying the Hadoop native libraries or symlinking at <filename>lib/native/Linux-amd64-64</filename>
     will ensure they are found.  Check with the Hadoop <filename>NativeLibraryChecker</filename>. 
    </para>

    <para>Here is example of how to point at the Hadoop libs with <varname>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</varname>
      environment variable:
      <programlisting>$ LD_LIBRARY_PATH=~/hadoop-2.5.0-SNAPSHOT/lib/native ./bin/hbase --config ~/conf_hbase org.apache.hadoop.util.NativeLibraryChecker
2014-08-26 13:42:49,332 INFO  [main] bzip2.Bzip2Factory: Successfully loaded &amp; initialized native-bzip2 library system-native
2014-08-26 13:42:49,337 INFO  [main] zlib.ZlibFactory: Successfully loaded &amp; initialized native-zlib library
Native library checking:
hadoop: true /home/stack/hadoop-2.5.0-SNAPSHOT/lib/native/libhadoop.so.1.0.0
zlib:   true /lib64/libz.so.1
snappy: true /usr/lib64/libsnappy.so.1
lz4:    true revision:99
bzip2:  true /lib64/libbz2.so.1</programlisting>
Set in <filename>hbase-env.sh</filename> the LD_LIBRARY_PATH environment variable when starting your HBase.
    </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Compressor Configuration, Installation, and Use</title>
      <section
        xml:id="compressor.install">
        <title>Configure HBase For Compressors</title>
        <para>Before HBase can use a given compressor, its libraries need to be available. Due to
          licensing issues, only GZ compression is available to HBase (via native Java libraries) in
          a default installation. Other compression libraries are available via the shared library
          bundled with your hadoop.  The hadoop native library needs to be findable when HBase
          starts.  See </para>
        <section>
          <title>Compressor Support On the Master</title>
          <para>A new configuration setting was introduced in HBase 0.95, to check the Master to
            determine which data block encoders are installed and configured on it, and assume that
            the entire cluster is configured the same. This option,
              <code>hbase.master.check.compression</code>, defaults to <literal>true</literal>. This
            prevents the situation described in <link
              xlink:href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HBASE-6370">HBASE-6370</link>, where
            a table is created or modified to support a codec that a region server does not support,
            leading to failures that take a long time to occur and are difficult to debug. </para>
          <para>If <code>hbase.master.check.compression</code> is enabled, libraries for all desired
            compressors need to be installed and configured on the Master, even if the Master does
            not run a region server.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Install GZ Support Via Native Libraries</title>
          <para>HBase uses Java's built-in GZip support unless the native Hadoop libraries are
            available on the CLASSPATH. The recommended way to add libraries to the CLASSPATH is to
            set the environment variable <envar>HBASE_LIBRARY_PATH</envar> for the user running
            HBase. If native libraries are not available and Java's GZIP is used, <literal>Got
              brand-new compressor</literal> reports will be present in the logs. See <xref
              linkend="brand.new.compressor" />).</para>
        </section>
        <section
          xml:id="lzo.compression">
          <title>Install LZO Support</title>
          <para>HBase cannot ship with LZO because of incompatibility between HBase, which uses an
            Apache Software License (ASL) and LZO, which uses a GPL license. See the <link
              xlink:href="http://wiki.apache.org/hadoop/UsingLzoCompression">Using LZO
              Compression</link> wiki page for information on configuring LZO support for HBase. </para>
          <para>If you depend upon LZO compression, consider configuring your RegionServers to fail
            to start if LZO is not available. See <xref
              linkend="hbase.regionserver.codecs" />.</para>
        </section>
        <section
          xml:id="lz4.compression">
          <title>Configure LZ4 Support</title>
          <para>LZ4 support is bundled with Hadoop. Make sure the hadoop shared library
            (libhadoop.so) is accessible when you start
            HBase. After configuring your platform (see <xref
              linkend="hbase.native.platform" />), you can make a symbolic link from HBase to the native Hadoop
            libraries. This assumes the two software installs are colocated. For example, if my
            'platform' is Linux-amd64-64:
            <programlisting language="bourne">$ cd $HBASE_HOME
$ mkdir lib/native
$ ln -s $HADOOP_HOME/lib/native lib/native/Linux-amd64-64</programlisting>
            Use the compression tool to check that LZ4 is installed on all nodes. Start up (or restart)
            HBase. Afterward, you can create and alter tables to enable LZ4 as a
            compression codec.:
            <screen>
hbase(main):003:0> <userinput>alter 'TestTable', {NAME => 'info', COMPRESSION => 'LZ4'}</userinput>
            </screen>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section
          xml:id="snappy.compression.installation">
          <title>Install Snappy Support</title>
          <para>HBase does not ship with Snappy support because of licensing issues. You can install
            Snappy binaries (for instance, by using <command>yum install snappy</command> on CentOS)
            or build Snappy from source. After installing Snappy, search for the shared library,
            which will be called <filename>libsnappy.so.X</filename> where X is a number. If you
            built from source, copy the shared library to a known location on your system, such as
              <filename>/opt/snappy/lib/</filename>.</para>
          <para>In addition to the Snappy library, HBase also needs access to the Hadoop shared
            library, which will be called something like <filename>libhadoop.so.X.Y</filename>,
            where X and Y are both numbers. Make note of the location of the Hadoop library, or copy
            it to the same location as the Snappy library.</para>
          <note>
            <para>The Snappy and Hadoop libraries need to be available on each node of your cluster.
              See <xref
                linkend="compression.test" /> to find out how to test that this is the case.</para>
            <para>See <xref
                linkend="hbase.regionserver.codecs" /> to configure your RegionServers to fail to
              start if a given compressor is not available.</para>
          </note>
          <para>Each of these library locations need to be added to the environment variable
              <envar>HBASE_LIBRARY_PATH</envar> for the operating system user that runs HBase. You
            need to restart the RegionServer for the changes to take effect.</para>
        </section>


        <section
          xml:id="compression.test">
          <title>CompressionTest</title>
          <para>You can use the CompressionTest tool to verify that your compressor is available to
            HBase:</para>
          <screen language="bourne">
 $ hbase org.apache.hadoop.hbase.util.CompressionTest hdfs://<replaceable>host/path/to/hbase</replaceable> snappy       
          </screen>
        </section>


        <section
          xml:id="hbase.regionserver.codecs">
          <title>Enforce Compression Settings On a RegionServer</title>
          <para>You can configure a RegionServer so that it will fail to restart if compression is
            configured incorrectly, by adding the option hbase.regionserver.codecs to the
              <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>, and setting its value to a comma-separated list
            of codecs that need to be available. For example, if you set this property to
              <literal>lzo,gz</literal>, the RegionServer would fail to start if both compressors
            were not available. This would prevent a new server from being added to the cluster
            without having codecs configured properly.</para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section
        xml:id="changing.compression">
        <title>Enable Compression On a ColumnFamily</title>
        <para>To enable compression for a ColumnFamily, use an <code>alter</code> command. You do
          not need to re-create the table or copy data. If you are changing codecs, be sure the old
          codec is still available until all the old StoreFiles have been compacted.</para>
        <example>
          <title>Enabling Compression on a ColumnFamily of an Existing Table using HBase
            Shell</title>
          <screen><![CDATA[
hbase> disable 'test'
hbase> alter 'test', {NAME => 'cf', COMPRESSION => 'GZ'}
hbase> enable 'test']]>
        </screen>
        </example>
        <example>
          <title>Creating a New Table with Compression On a ColumnFamily</title>
          <screen><![CDATA[
hbase> create 'test2', { NAME => 'cf2', COMPRESSION => 'SNAPPY' }         
          ]]></screen>
        </example>
        <example>
          <title>Verifying a ColumnFamily's Compression Settings</title>
          <screen><![CDATA[
hbase> describe 'test'
DESCRIPTION                                          ENABLED
 'test', {NAME => 'cf', DATA_BLOCK_ENCODING => 'NONE false
 ', BLOOMFILTER => 'ROW', REPLICATION_SCOPE => '0',
 VERSIONS => '1', COMPRESSION => 'GZ', MIN_VERSIONS
 => '0', TTL => 'FOREVER', KEEP_DELETED_CELLS => 'fa
 lse', BLOCKSIZE => '65536', IN_MEMORY => 'false', B
 LOCKCACHE => 'true'}
1 row(s) in 0.1070 seconds
          ]]></screen>
        </example>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Testing Compression Performance</title>
        <para>HBase includes a tool called LoadTestTool which provides mechanisms to test your
          compression performance. You must specify either <literal>-write</literal> or
          <literal>-update-read</literal> as your first parameter, and if you do not specify another
        parameter, usage advice is printed for each option.</para>
        <example>
          <title><command>LoadTestTool</command> Usage</title>
          <screen language="bourne"><![CDATA[
$ bin/hbase org.apache.hadoop.hbase.util.LoadTestTool -h            
usage: bin/hbase org.apache.hadoop.hbase.util.LoadTestTool <options>
Options:
 -batchupdate                 Whether to use batch as opposed to separate
                              updates for every column in a row
 -bloom <arg>                 Bloom filter type, one of [NONE, ROW, ROWCOL]
 -compression <arg>           Compression type, one of [LZO, GZ, NONE, SNAPPY,
                              LZ4]
 -data_block_encoding <arg>   Encoding algorithm (e.g. prefix compression) to
                              use for data blocks in the test column family, one
                              of [NONE, PREFIX, DIFF, FAST_DIFF, PREFIX_TREE].
 -encryption <arg>            Enables transparent encryption on the test table,
                              one of [AES]
 -generator <arg>             The class which generates load for the tool. Any
                              args for this class can be passed as colon
                              separated after class name
 -h,--help                    Show usage
 -in_memory                   Tries to keep the HFiles of the CF inmemory as far
                              as possible.  Not guaranteed that reads are always
                              served from inmemory
 -init_only                   Initialize the test table only, don't do any
                              loading
 -key_window <arg>            The 'key window' to maintain between reads and
                              writes for concurrent write/read workload. The
                              default is 0.
 -max_read_errors <arg>       The maximum number of read errors to tolerate
                              before terminating all reader threads. The default
                              is 10.
 -multiput                    Whether to use multi-puts as opposed to separate
                              puts for every column in a row
 -num_keys <arg>              The number of keys to read/write
 -num_tables <arg>            A positive integer number. When a number n is
                              speicfied, load test tool  will load n table
                              parallely. -tn parameter value becomes table name
                              prefix. Each table name is in format
                              <tn>_1...<tn>_n
 -read <arg>                  <verify_percent>[:<#threads=20>]
 -regions_per_server <arg>    A positive integer number. When a number n is
                              specified, load test tool will create the test
                              table with n regions per server
 -skip_init                   Skip the initialization; assume test table already
                              exists
 -start_key <arg>             The first key to read/write (a 0-based index). The
                              default value is 0.
 -tn <arg>                    The name of the table to read or write
 -update <arg>                <update_percent>[:<#threads=20>][:<#whether to
                              ignore nonce collisions=0>]
 -write <arg>                 <avg_cols_per_key>:<avg_data_size>[:<#threads=20>]
 -zk <arg>                    ZK quorum as comma-separated host names without
                              port numbers
 -zk_root <arg>               name of parent znode in zookeeper            
          ]]></screen>
        </example>
        <example>
          <title>Example Usage of LoadTestTool</title>
          <screen language="bourne">
$ hbase org.apache.hadoop.hbase.util.LoadTestTool -write 1:10:100 -num_keys 1000000
          -read 100:30 -num_tables 1 -data_block_encoding NONE -tn load_test_tool_NONE
          </screen>
        </example>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="data.block.encoding.enable">
      <title>Enable Data Block Encoding</title>
      <para>Codecs are built into HBase so no extra configuration is needed. Codecs are enabled on a
        table by setting the <code>DATA_BLOCK_ENCODING</code> property. Disable the table before
        altering its DATA_BLOCK_ENCODING setting. Following is an example using HBase Shell:</para>
      <example>
        <title>Enable Data Block Encoding On a Table</title>
        <screen><![CDATA[
hbase>  disable 'test'
hbase> alter 'test', { NAME => 'cf', DATA_BLOCK_ENCODING => 'FAST_DIFF' }
Updating all regions with the new schema...
0/1 regions updated.
1/1 regions updated.
Done.
0 row(s) in 2.2820 seconds
hbase> enable 'test'
0 row(s) in 0.1580 seconds          
          ]]></screen>
      </example>
      <example>
        <title>Verifying a ColumnFamily's Data Block Encoding</title>
        <screen><![CDATA[
hbase> describe 'test'
DESCRIPTION                                          ENABLED
 'test', {NAME => 'cf', DATA_BLOCK_ENCODING => 'FAST true
 _DIFF', BLOOMFILTER => 'ROW', REPLICATION_SCOPE =>
 '0', VERSIONS => '1', COMPRESSION => 'GZ', MIN_VERS
 IONS => '0', TTL => 'FOREVER', KEEP_DELETED_CELLS =
 > 'false', BLOCKSIZE => '65536', IN_MEMORY => 'fals
 e', BLOCKCACHE => 'true'}
1 row(s) in 0.0650 seconds          
        ]]></screen>
      </example>
    </section>
  

</appendix>
