<?xml version="1.0"?>
<chapter
  xml:id="configuration"
  version="5.0"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
  xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
  xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
  xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <!--
/**
 * Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 * or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 * distributed with this work for additional information
 * regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 * to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 * "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 * with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 *
 *     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 *
 * Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 * distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 * WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 * See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 * limitations under the License.
 */
-->
  <title>Apache HBase Configuration</title>
  <para>This chapter expands upon the <xref linkend="getting_started" /> chapter to further explain
    configuration of Apache HBase. Please read this chapter carefully, especially <xref
      linkend="basic.prerequisites" /> to ensure that your HBase testing and deployment goes
    smoothly, and prevent data loss.</para>

  <para> Apache HBase uses the same configuration system as Apache Hadoop. All configuration files
    are located in the <filename>conf/</filename> directory, which needs to be kept in sync for each
    node on your cluster.</para>
  
  <variablelist>
    <title>HBase Configuration Files</title>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><filename>backup-masters</filename></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Not present by default. A plain-text file which lists hosts on which the Master should
          start a backup Master process, one host per line.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><filename>hadoop-metrics2-hbase.properties</filename></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Used to connect HBase Hadoop's Metrics2 framework. See the <link
            xlink:href="http://wiki.apache.org/hadoop/HADOOP-6728-MetricsV2">Hadoop Wiki
            entry</link> for more information on Metrics2. Contains only commented-out examples by
          default.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><filename>hbase-env.cmd</filename> and <filename>hbase-env.sh</filename></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Script for Windows and Linux / Unix environments to set up the working environment for
        HBase, including the location of Java, Java options, and other environment variables. The
        file contains many commented-out examples to provide guidance.</para>
        <note>
          <para>In HBase 0.98.5 and newer, you must set <envar>JAVA_HOME</envar> on each node of
            your cluster. <filename>hbase-env.sh</filename> provides a handy mechanism to do
            this.</para>
        </note>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><filename>hbase-policy.xml</filename></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>The default policy configuration file used by RPC servers to make authorization
          decisions on client requests. Only used if HBase security (<xref
            linkend="security" />) is enabled.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><filename>hbase-site.xml</filename></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>The main HBase configuration file. This file specifies configuration options which
          override HBase's default configuration. You can view (but do not edit) the default
          configuration file at <filename>docs/hbase-default.xml</filename>. You can also view the
          entire effective configuration for your cluster (defaults and overrides) in the
            <guilabel>HBase Configuration</guilabel> tab of the HBase Web UI.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><filename>log4j.properties</filename></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Configuration file for HBase logging via <code>log4j</code>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><filename>regionservers</filename></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>A plain-text file containing a list of hosts which should run a RegionServer in your
          HBase cluster. By default this file contains the single entry
          <literal>localhost</literal>. It should contain a list of hostnames or IP addresses, one
          per line, and should only contain <literal>localhost</literal> if each node in your
          cluster will run a RegionServer on its <literal>localhost</literal> interface.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  
  <tip>
    <title>Checking XML Validity</title>
    <para>When you edit XML, it is a good idea to use an XML-aware editor to be sure that your
      syntax is correct and your XML is well-formed. You can also use the <command>xmllint</command>
      utility to check that your XML is well-formed. By default, <command>xmllint</command> re-flows
      and prints the XML to standard output. To check for well-formedness and only print output if
      errors exist, use the command <command>xmllint -noout
        <replaceable>filename.xml</replaceable></command>.</para>
  </tip>

  <warning>
    <title>Keep Configuration In Sync Across the Cluster</title>
    <para>When running in distributed mode, after you make an edit to an HBase configuration, make
      sure you copy the content of the <filename>conf/</filename> directory to all nodes of the
      cluster. HBase will not do this for you. Use <command>rsync</command>, <command>scp</command>,
      or another secure mechanism for copying the configuration files to your nodes. For most
      configuration, a restart is needed for servers to pick up changes An exception is dynamic
      configuration. to be described later below.</para>
  </warning>

  <section
    xml:id="basic.prerequisites">
    <title>Basic Prerequisites</title>
    <para>This section lists required services and some required system configuration. </para>

    <table
      xml:id="java">
      <title>Java</title>
      <textobject>
        <para>HBase requires at least Java 6 from <link
            xlink:href="http://www.java.com/download/">Oracle</link>. The following table lists
          which JDK version are compatible with each version of HBase.</para>
      </textobject>
      <tgroup
        cols="4">
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>HBase Version</entry>
            <entry>JDK 6</entry>
            <entry>JDK 7</entry>
            <entry>JDK 8</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>1.0</entry>
            <entry><link
                xlink:href="http://search-hadoop.com/m/DHED4Zlz0R1">Not Supported</link></entry>
            <entry>yes</entry>
            <entry><para>Running with JDK 8 will work but is not well tested.</para></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>0.98</entry>
            <entry>yes</entry>
            <entry>yes</entry>
            <entry><para>Running with JDK 8 works but is not well tested. Building with JDK 8 would
                require removal of the deprecated remove() method of the PoolMap class and is under
                consideration. See ee <link
                  xlink:href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HBASE-7608">HBASE-7608</link>
                for more information about JDK 8 support.</para></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>0.96</entry>
            <entry>yes</entry>
            <entry>yes</entry>
            <entry />
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>0.94</entry>
            <entry>yes</entry>
            <entry>yes</entry>
            <entry />
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <note>
      <para>In HBase 0.98.5 and newer, you must set <envar>JAVA_HOME</envar> on each node of
        your cluster. <filename>hbase-env.sh</filename> provides a handy mechanism to do
        this.</para>
    </note>
    
    <variablelist
      xml:id="os">
      <title>Operating System Utilities</title>
      <varlistentry
        xml:id="ssh">
        <term>ssh</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>HBase uses the Secure Shell (ssh) command and utilities extensively to communicate
            between cluster nodes. Each server in the cluster must be running <command>ssh</command>
            so that the Hadoop and HBase daemons can be managed. You must be able to connect to all
            nodes via SSH, including the local node, from the Master as well as any backup Master,
            using a shared key rather than a password. You can see the basic methodology for such a
            set-up in Linux or Unix systems at <xref
              linkend="passwordless.ssh.quickstart" />. If your cluster nodes use OS X, see the
            section, <link
              xlink:href="http://wiki.apache.org/hadoop/Running_Hadoop_On_OS_X_10.5_64-bit_%28Single-Node_Cluster%29">SSH:
              Setting up Remote Desktop and Enabling Self-Login</link> on the Hadoop wiki.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry
        xml:id="dns">
        <term>DNS</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>HBase uses the local hostname to self-report its IP address. Both forward and
            reverse DNS resolving must work in versions of HBase previous to 0.92.0. The <link
                  xlink:href="https://github.com/sujee/hadoop-dns-checker">hadoop-dns-checker</link>
                tool can be used to verify DNS is working correctly on the cluster. The project
                README file provides detailed instructions on usage. </para>

          <para>If your server has multiple network interfaces, HBase defaults to using the
            interface that the primary hostname resolves to. To override this behavior, set the
              <code>hbase.regionserver.dns.interface</code> property to a different interface. This
            will only work if each server in your cluster uses the same network interface
            configuration.</para>

          <para>To choose a different DNS nameserver than the system default, set the
              <varname>hbase.regionserver.dns.nameserver</varname> property to the IP address of
            that nameserver.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry
        xml:id="loopback.ip">
        <term>Loopback IP</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Prior to hbase-0.96.0, HBase only used the IP address
              <systemitem>127.0.0.1</systemitem> to refer to <code>localhost</code>, and this could
            not be configured. See <xref
              linkend="loopback.ip" />.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry
        xml:id="ntp">
        <term>NTP</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The clocks on cluster nodes should be synchronized. A small amount of variation is
            acceptable, but larger amounts of skew can cause erratic and unexpected behavior. Time
            synchronization is one of the first things to check if you see unexplained problems in
            your cluster. It is recommended that you run a Network Time Protocol (NTP) service, or
            another time-synchronization mechanism, on your cluster, and that all nodes look to the
            same service for time synchronization. See the <link
              xlink:href="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/sag/html/basic-ntp-config.html">Basic NTP
              Configuration</link> at <citetitle>The Linux Documentation Project (TLDP)</citetitle>
            to set up NTP.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry
        xml:id="ulimit">
        <term>Limits on Number of Files and Processes (<command>ulimit</command>)
          <indexterm>
            <primary>ulimit</primary>
          </indexterm><indexterm>
            <primary>nproc</primary>
          </indexterm>
        </term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Apache HBase is a database. It requires the ability to open a large number of files
            at once. Many Linux distributions limit the number of files a single user is allowed to
            open to <literal>1024</literal> (or <literal>256</literal> on older versions of OS X).
            You can check this limit on your servers by running the command <command>ulimit
              -n</command> when logged in as the user which runs HBase. See <xref
              linkend="trouble.rs.runtime.filehandles" /> for some of the problems you may
            experience if the limit is too low. You may also notice errors such as the
            following:</para>
          <screen>
2010-04-06 03:04:37,542 INFO org.apache.hadoop.hdfs.DFSClient: Exception increateBlockOutputStream java.io.EOFException
2010-04-06 03:04:37,542 INFO org.apache.hadoop.hdfs.DFSClient: Abandoning block blk_-6935524980745310745_1391901
          </screen>
          <para>It is recommended to raise the ulimit to at least 10,000, but more likely 10,240,
            because the value is usually expressed in multiples of 1024. Each ColumnFamily has at
            least one StoreFile, and possibly more than 6 StoreFiles if the region is under load.
            The number of open files required depends upon the number of ColumnFamilies and the
            number of regions. The following is a rough formula for calculating the potential number
            of open files on a RegionServer. </para>
          <example>
            <title>Calculate the Potential Number of Open Files</title>
            <screen>(StoreFiles per ColumnFamily) x (regions per RegionServer)</screen>
          </example>
          <para>For example, assuming that a schema had 3 ColumnFamilies per region with an average
            of 3 StoreFiles per ColumnFamily, and there are 100 regions per RegionServer, the JVM
            will open 3 * 3 * 100 = 900 file descriptors, not counting open JAR files, configuration
            files, and others. Opening a file does not take many resources, and the risk of allowing
            a user to open too many files is minimal.</para>
          <para>Another related setting is the number of processes a user is allowed to run at once.
            In Linux and Unix, the number of processes is set using the <command>ulimit -u</command>
            command. This should not be confused with the <command>nproc</command> command, which
            controls the number of CPUs available to a given user. Under load, a
              <varname>nproc</varname> that is too low can cause OutOfMemoryError exceptions. See
            Jack Levin's <link
              xlink:href="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.comp.java.hadoop.hbase.user/16374">major
              hdfs issues</link> thread on the hbase-users mailing list, from 2011.</para>
          <para>Configuring the fmaximum number of ile descriptors and processes for the user who is
            running the HBase process is an operating system configuration, rather than an HBase
            configuration. It is also important to be sure that the settings are changed for the
            user that actually runs HBase. To see which user started HBase, and that user's ulimit
            configuration, look at the first line of the HBase log for that instance. A useful read
            setting config on you hadoop cluster is Aaron Kimballs' <link
              xlink:href="http://www.cloudera.com/blog/2009/03/configuration-parameters-what-can-you-just-ignore/"
              >Configuration Parameters: What can you just ignore?</link></para>
          <formalpara xml:id="ulimit_ubuntu">
            <title><command>ulimit</command> Settings on Ubuntu</title>
            <para>To configure <command>ulimit</command> settings on Ubuntu, edit
                <filename>/etc/security/limits.conf</filename>, which is a space-delimited file with
              four columns. Refer to the <link
                xlink:href="http://manpages.ubuntu.com/manpages/lucid/man5/limits.conf.5.html">man
                page for limits.conf</link> for details about the format of this file. In the
              following example, the first line sets both soft and hard limits for the number of
              open files (<literal>nofile</literal>) to <literal>32768</literal> for the operating
              system user with the username <literal>hadoop</literal>. The second line sets the
              number of processes to 32000 for the same user.</para>
          </formalpara>
          <screen>
hadoop  -       nofile  32768
hadoop  -       nproc   32000
          </screen>
          <para>The settings are only applied if the Pluggable Authentication Module (PAM)
            environment is directed to use them. To configure PAM to use these limits, be sure that
            the <filename>/etc/pam.d/common-session</filename> file contains the following line:</para>
          <screen>session required  pam_limits.so</screen>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry
        xml:id="windows">
        <term>Windows</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Prior to HBase 0.96, testing for running HBase on Microsoft Windows was limited.
            Running a on Windows nodes is not recommended for production systems.</para>

        <para>To run versions of HBase prior to 0.96 on Microsoft Windows, you must install <link
            xlink:href="http://cygwin.com/">Cygwin</link> and run HBase within the Cygwin
          environment. This provides support for Linux/Unix commands and scripts. The full details are explained in the <link
            xlink:href="http://hbase.apache.org/cygwin.html">Windows Installation</link> guide. Also <link
            xlink:href="http://search-hadoop.com/?q=hbase+windows&amp;fc_project=HBase&amp;fc_type=mail+_hash_+dev">search
            our user mailing list</link> to pick up latest fixes figured by Windows users.</para>
        <para>Post-hbase-0.96.0, hbase runs natively on windows with supporting
            <command>*.cmd</command> scripts bundled. </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>
    <!--  OS -->

    <section
      xml:id="hadoop">
      <title><link
          xlink:href="http://hadoop.apache.org">Hadoop</link><indexterm>
          <primary>Hadoop</primary>
        </indexterm></title>
      <para>The following table summarizes the versions of Hadoop supported with each version of
        HBase. Based on the version of HBase, you should select the most
        appropriate version of Hadoop. You can use Apache Hadoop, or a vendor's distribution of
        Hadoop. No distinction is made here. See <link
          xlink:href="http://wiki.apache.org/hadoop/Distributions%20and%20Commercial%20Support" />
        for information about vendors of Hadoop.</para>
      <tip>
        <title>Hadoop 2.x is recommended.</title>
        <para>Hadoop 2.x is faster and includes features, such as short-circuit reads, which will
          help improve your HBase random read profile. Hadoop 2.x also includes important bug fixes
          that will improve your overall HBase experience. HBase 0.98 drops support for Hadoop 1.0, deprecates use of Hadoop 1.1+,
          and HBase 1.0 will not support Hadoop 1.x.</para>
      </tip>
      <para>Use the following legend to interpret this table:</para>
      <simplelist
        type="vert"
        columns="1">
        <member>S = supported and tested,</member>
        <member>X = not supported,</member>
        <member>NT = it should run, but not tested enough.</member>
      </simplelist>

      <table>
        <title>Hadoop version support matrix</title>
        <tgroup
          cols="6"
          align="left"
          colsep="1"
          rowsep="1">
          <colspec
            colname="c1"
            align="left" />
          <colspec
            colname="c2"
            align="center" />
          <colspec
            colname="c3"
            align="center" />
          <colspec
            colname="c4"
            align="center" />
          <colspec
            colname="c5"
            align="center" />
          <colspec
            colname="c6"
            align="center" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry> </entry>
              <entry>HBase-0.92.x</entry>
              <entry>HBase-0.94.x</entry>
              <entry>HBase-0.96.x</entry>
              <entry><para>HBase-0.98.x (Support for Hadoop 1.1+ is deprecated.)</para></entry>
              <entry><para>HBase-1.0.x (Hadoop 1.x is NOT supported)</para></entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Hadoop-0.20.205</entry>
              <entry>S</entry>
              <entry>X</entry>
              <entry>X</entry>
              <entry>X</entry>
              <entry>X</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Hadoop-0.22.x </entry>
              <entry>S</entry>
              <entry>X</entry>
              <entry>X</entry>
              <entry>X</entry>
              <entry>X</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Hadoop-1.0.x</entry>
              <entry>X</entry>
              <entry>X</entry>
              <entry>X</entry>
              <entry>X</entry>
              <entry>X</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Hadoop-1.1.x </entry>
              <entry>NT</entry>
              <entry>S</entry>
              <entry>S</entry>
              <entry>NT</entry>
              <entry>X</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Hadoop-0.23.x </entry>
              <entry>X</entry>
              <entry>S</entry>
              <entry>NT</entry>
              <entry>X</entry>
              <entry>X</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Hadoop-2.0.x-alpha </entry>
              <entry>X</entry>
              <entry>NT</entry>
              <entry>X</entry>
              <entry>X</entry>
              <entry>X</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Hadoop-2.1.0-beta </entry>
              <entry>X</entry>
              <entry>NT</entry>
              <entry>S</entry>
              <entry>X</entry>
              <entry>X</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Hadoop-2.2.0 </entry>
              <entry>X</entry>
              <entry><link linkend="hadoop2.hbase-0.94">NT</link></entry>
              <entry>S</entry>
              <entry>S</entry>
              <entry>NT</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Hadoop-2.3.x</entry>
              <entry>X</entry>
              <entry>NT</entry>
              <entry>S</entry>
              <entry>S</entry>
              <entry>NT</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Hadoop-2.4.x</entry>
              <entry>X</entry>
              <entry>NT</entry>
              <entry>S</entry>
              <entry>S</entry>
              <entry>S</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Hadoop-2.5.x</entry>
              <entry>X</entry>
              <entry>NT</entry>
              <entry>S</entry>
              <entry>S</entry>
              <entry>S</entry>
            </row>

          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <note
        xml:id="replace.hadoop">
        <title>Replace the Hadoop Bundled With HBase!</title>
        <para> Because HBase depends on Hadoop, it bundles an instance of the Hadoop jar under its
            <filename>lib</filename> directory. The bundled jar is ONLY for use in standalone mode.
          In distributed mode, it is <emphasis>critical</emphasis> that the version of Hadoop that
          is out on your cluster match what is under HBase. Replace the hadoop jar found in the
          HBase lib directory with the hadoop jar you are running on your cluster to avoid version
          mismatch issues. Make sure you replace the jar in HBase everywhere on your cluster. Hadoop
          version mismatch issues have various manifestations but often all looks like its hung up.
        </para>
      </note>
      <section
        xml:id="hadoop2.hbase-0.94">
        <title>Apache HBase 0.94 with Hadoop 2</title>
        <para>To get 0.94.x to run on hadoop 2.2.0, you need to change the hadoop
        2 and protobuf versions in the <filename>pom.xml</filename>: Here is a diff with
        pom.xml changes: </para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[$ svn diff pom.xml
Index: pom.xml
===================================================================
--- pom.xml     (revision 1545157)
+++ pom.xml     (working copy)
@@ -1034,7 +1034,7 @@
     <slf4j.version>1.4.3</slf4j.version>
     <log4j.version>1.2.16</log4j.version>
     <mockito-all.version>1.8.5</mockito-all.version>
-    <protobuf.version>2.4.0a</protobuf.version>
+    <protobuf.version>2.5.0</protobuf.version>
     <stax-api.version>1.0.1</stax-api.version>
     <thrift.version>0.8.0</thrift.version>
     <zookeeper.version>3.4.5</zookeeper.version>
@@ -2241,7 +2241,7 @@
         </property>
       </activation>
       <properties>
-        <hadoop.version>2.0.0-alpha</hadoop.version>
+        <hadoop.version>2.2.0</hadoop.version>
         <slf4j.version>1.6.1</slf4j.version>
       </properties>
       <dependencies>]]>
                   </programlisting>
                  <para>The next step is to regenerate Protobuf files and assuming that the Protobuf
                    has been installed:</para>
                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Go to the hbase root folder, using the command line;</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Type the following commands:</para>
                      <para>
                        <programlisting language="bourne"><![CDATA[$ protoc -Isrc/main/protobuf --java_out=src/main/java src/main/protobuf/hbase.proto]]></programlisting>
                      </para>
                      <para>
                        <programlisting language="bourne"><![CDATA[$ protoc -Isrc/main/protobuf --java_out=src/main/java src/main/protobuf/ErrorHandling.proto]]></programlisting>
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                  <para> Building against the hadoop 2 profile by running something like the
                    following command: </para>
                  <screen language="bourne">$  mvn clean install assembly:single -Dhadoop.profile=2.0 -DskipTests</screen>
      </section>
      <section
        xml:id="hadoop.hbase-0.94">
        <title>Apache HBase 0.92 and 0.94</title>
        <para>HBase 0.92 and 0.94 versions can work with Hadoop versions, 0.20.205, 0.22.x, 1.0.x,
          and 1.1.x. HBase-0.94 can additionally work with Hadoop-0.23.x and 2.x, but you may have
          to recompile the code using the specific maven profile (see top level pom.xml)</para>
      </section>

      <section
        xml:id="hadoop.hbase-0.96">
        <title>Apache HBase 0.96</title>
        <para> As of Apache HBase 0.96.x, Apache Hadoop 1.0.x at least is required. Hadoop 2 is
          strongly encouraged (faster but also has fixes that help MTTR). We will no longer run
          properly on older Hadoops such as 0.20.205 or branch-0.20-append. Do not move to Apache
          HBase 0.96.x if you cannot upgrade your Hadoop.. See <link
                xlink:href="http://search-hadoop.com/m/7vFVx4EsUb2">HBase, mail # dev - DISCUSS:
                Have hbase require at least hadoop 1.0.0 in hbase 0.96.0?</link></para>
      </section>

      <section
        xml:id="hadoop.older.versions">
        <title>Hadoop versions 0.20.x - 1.x</title>
        <para> HBase will lose data unless it is running on an HDFS that has a durable
            <code>sync</code> implementation. DO NOT use Hadoop 0.20.2, Hadoop 0.20.203.0, and
          Hadoop 0.20.204.0 which DO NOT have this attribute. Currently only Hadoop versions
          0.20.205.x or any release in excess of this version -- this includes hadoop-1.0.0 -- have
          a working, durable sync. The Cloudera blog post <link
            xlink:href="http://www.cloudera.com/blog/2012/01/an-update-on-apache-hadoop-1-0/">An
            update on Apache Hadoop 1.0</link> by Charles Zedlweski has a nice exposition on how all
          the Hadoop versions relate. Its worth checking out if you are having trouble making sense
          of the Hadoop version morass. </para>
        <para>Sync has to be explicitly enabled by setting
            <varname>dfs.support.append</varname> equal to true on both the client side -- in
            <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename> -- and on the serverside in
            <filename>hdfs-site.xml</filename> (The sync facility HBase needs is a subset of the
          append code path).</para>
        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[  
<property>
  <name>dfs.support.append</name>
  <value>true</value>
</property>]]></programlisting>
        <para> You will have to restart your cluster after making this edit. Ignore the
          chicken-little comment you'll find in the <filename>hdfs-default.xml</filename> in the
          description for the <varname>dfs.support.append</varname> configuration. </para>
      </section>
      <section
        xml:id="hadoop.security">
        <title>Apache HBase on Secure Hadoop</title>
        <para>Apache HBase will run on any Hadoop 0.20.x that incorporates Hadoop security features
          as long as you do as suggested above and replace the Hadoop jar that ships with HBase with
          the secure version. If you want to read more about how to setup Secure HBase, see <xref
            linkend="hbase.secure.configuration" />.</para>
      </section>

      <section
        xml:id="dfs.datanode.max.transfer.threads">
        <title><varname>dfs.datanode.max.transfer.threads</varname><indexterm>
            <primary>dfs.datanode.max.transfer.threads</primary>
          </indexterm></title>

        <para>An HDFS datanode has an upper bound on the number of files that it will serve
          at any one time. Before doing any loading, make sure you have configured
          Hadoop's <filename>conf/hdfs-site.xml</filename>, setting the
          <varname>dfs.datanode.max.transfer.threads</varname> value to at least the following:
        </para>
        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<property>
  <name>dfs.datanode.max.transfer.threads</name>
  <value>4096</value>
</property>
      ]]></programlisting>

        <para>Be sure to restart your HDFS after making the above configuration.</para>

        <para>Not having this configuration in place makes for strange-looking failures. One
        manifestation is a complaint about missing blocks. For example:</para>
        <screen>10/12/08 20:10:31 INFO hdfs.DFSClient: Could not obtain block
          blk_XXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXX_YYYYYYYY from any node: java.io.IOException: No live nodes
          contain current block. Will get new block locations from namenode and retry...</screen>
        <para>See also <xref linkend="casestudies.max.transfer.threads" /> and note that this
          property was previously known as <varname>dfs.datanode.max.xcievers</varname> (e.g.
          <link
            xlink:href="http://ccgtech.blogspot.com/2010/02/hadoop-hdfs-deceived-by-xciever.html">
            Hadoop HDFS: Deceived by Xciever</link>).
        </para>


      </section>
    </section>
    <!--  hadoop -->
    <section xml:id="zookeeper.requirements">
      <title>ZooKeeper Requirements</title>
      <para>ZooKeeper 3.4.x is required as of HBase 1.0.0. HBase makes use of the
        <methodname>multi</methodname> functionality that is only available since 3.4.0
        (The <property>useMulti</property> is defaulted true in HBase 1.0.0).
        See <link href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HBASE-12241">HBASE-12241 The crash of regionServer when taking deadserver's replication queue breaks replication</link>
        and <link href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HBASE-6775">Use ZK.multi when available for HBASE-6710 0.92/0.94 compatibility fix</link> for background.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section
    xml:id="standalone_dist">
    <title>HBase run modes: Standalone and Distributed</title>

    <para>HBase has two run modes: <xref
        linkend="standalone" /> and <xref
        linkend="distributed" />. Out of the box, HBase runs in standalone mode. Whatever your mode,
      you will need to configure HBase by editing files in the HBase <filename>conf</filename>
      directory. At a minimum, you must edit <code>conf/hbase-env.sh</code> to tell HBase which
        <command>java</command> to use. In this file you set HBase environment variables such as the
      heapsize and other options for the <application>JVM</application>, the preferred location for
      log files, etc. Set <varname>JAVA_HOME</varname> to point at the root of your
        <command>java</command> install.</para>

    <section
      xml:id="standalone">
      <title>Standalone HBase</title>

      <para>This is the default mode. Standalone mode is what is described in the <xref
          linkend="quickstart" /> section. In standalone mode, HBase does not use HDFS -- it uses
        the local filesystem instead -- and it runs all HBase daemons and a local ZooKeeper all up
        in the same JVM. Zookeeper binds to a well known port so clients may talk to HBase.</para>
    </section>

    <section
      xml:id="distributed">
      <title>Distributed</title>

      <para>Distributed mode can be subdivided into distributed but all daemons run on a single node
        -- a.k.a <emphasis>pseudo-distributed</emphasis>-- and
          <emphasis>fully-distributed</emphasis> where the daemons are spread across all nodes in
        the cluster. The pseudo-distributed vs fully-distributed nomenclature comes from Hadoop.</para>

      <para>Pseudo-distributed mode can run against the local filesystem or it can run against an
        instance of the <emphasis>Hadoop Distributed File System</emphasis> (HDFS).
        Fully-distributed mode can ONLY run on HDFS. See the Hadoop <link
          xlink:href="http://hadoop.apache.org/common/docs/r1.1.1/api/overview-summary.html#overview_description">
          requirements and instructions</link> for how to set up HDFS for Hadoop 1.x. A good
        walk-through for setting up HDFS on Hadoop 2 is at <link
          xlink:href="http://www.alexjf.net/blog/distributed-systems/hadoop-yarn-installation-definitive-guide">http://www.alexjf.net/blog/distributed-systems/hadoop-yarn-installation-definitive-guide</link>.</para>

      <para>Below we describe the different distributed setups. Starting, verification and
        exploration of your install, whether a <emphasis>pseudo-distributed</emphasis> or
          <emphasis>fully-distributed</emphasis> configuration is described in a section that
        follows, <xref
          linkend="confirm" />. The same verification script applies to both deploy types.</para>
      <section
        xml:id="pseudo">
        <title>Pseudo-distributed</title>
        <note>
          <title>Pseudo-Distributed Quickstart</title>
          <para>A quickstart has been added to the <xref
              linkend="quickstart" /> chapter. See <xref
              linkend="quickstart-pseudo" />. Some of the information that was originally in this
            section has been moved there.</para>
        </note>

        <para>A pseudo-distributed mode is simply a fully-distributed mode run on a single host. Use
          this configuration testing and prototyping on HBase. Do not use this configuration for
          production nor for evaluating HBase performance.</para>

      </section>

    </section>

    <section
      xml:id="fully_dist">
      <title>Fully-distributed</title>
      <para>By default, HBase runs in standalone mode. Both standalone mode and pseudo-distributed
        mode are provided for the purposes of small-scale testing. For a production environment,
        distributed mode is appropriate. In distributed mode, multiple instances of HBase daemons
        run on multiple servers in the cluster.</para>
      <para>Just as in pseudo-distributed mode, a fully distributed configuration requires that you
        set the <code>hbase-cluster.distributed</code> property to <literal>true</literal>.
        Typically, the <code>hbase.rootdir</code> is configured to point to a highly-available HDFS
        filesystem. </para>
      <para>In addition, the cluster is configured so that multiple cluster nodes enlist as
        RegionServers, ZooKeeper QuorumPeers, and backup HMaster servers. These configuration basics
        are all demonstrated in <xref
          linkend="quickstart-fully-distributed" />.</para>

      <formalpara
        xml:id="regionserver">
        <title>Distributed RegionServers</title>
        <para>Typically, your cluster will contain multiple RegionServers all running on different
          servers, as well as primary and backup Master and Zookeeper daemons. The
            <filename>conf/regionservers</filename> file on the master server contains a list of
          hosts whose RegionServers are associated with this cluster. Each host is on a separate
          line. All hosts listed in this file will have their RegionServer processes started and
          stopped when the master server starts or stops.</para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara
        xml:id="hbase.zookeeper">
        <title>ZooKeeper and HBase</title>
        <para>See section <xref
            linkend="zookeeper" /> for ZooKeeper setup for HBase.</para>
      </formalpara>

      <example>
        <title>Example Distributed HBase Cluster</title>
        <para>This is a bare-bones <filename>conf/hbase-site.xml</filename> for a distributed HBase
          cluster. A cluster that is used for real-world work would contain more custom
          configuration parameters. Most HBase configuration directives have default values, which
          are used unless the value is overridden in the <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>. See <xref
            linkend="config.files" /> for more information.</para>
        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<configuration>
  <property>
    <name>hbase.rootdir</name>
    <value>hdfs://namenode.example.org:8020/hbase</value>
  </property>
  <property>
    <name>hbase.cluster.distributed</name>
    <value>true</value>
  </property>
  <property>
      <name>hbase.zookeeper.quorum</name>
      <value>node-a.example.com,node-b.example.com,node-c.example.com</value>
    </property>
</configuration>
]]>
        </programlisting>
        <para>This is an example <filename>conf/regionservers</filename> file, which contains a list
          of each node that should run a RegionServer in the cluster. These nodes need HBase
          installed and they need to use the same contents of the <filename>conf/</filename>
          directory as the Master server..</para>
        <programlisting>
node-a.example.com
node-b.example.com
node-c.example.com
        </programlisting>
        <para>This is an example <filename>conf/backup-masters</filename> file, which contains a
          list of each node that should run a backup Master instance. The backup Master instances
          will sit idle unless the main Master becomes unavailable.</para>
        <programlisting>
node-b.example.com
node-c.example.com
        </programlisting>
      </example>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Distributed HBase Quickstart</title>
        <para>See <xref
            linkend="quickstart-fully-distributed" /> for a walk-through of a simple three-node
          cluster configuration with multiple ZooKeeper, backup HMaster, and RegionServer
          instances.</para>
      </formalpara>

      <procedure
        xml:id="hdfs_client_conf">
        <title>HDFS Client Configuration</title>
        <step>
          <para>Of note, if you have made HDFS client configuration on your Hadoop cluster, such as
            configuration directives for HDFS clients, as opposed to server-side configurations, you
            must use one of the following methods to enable HBase to see and use these configuration
            changes:</para>
          <stepalternatives>
            <step>
              <para>Add a pointer to your <varname>HADOOP_CONF_DIR</varname> to the
                  <varname>HBASE_CLASSPATH</varname> environment variable in
                  <filename>hbase-env.sh</filename>.</para>
            </step>

            <step>
              <para>Add a copy of <filename>hdfs-site.xml</filename> (or
                  <filename>hadoop-site.xml</filename>) or, better, symlinks, under
                  <filename>${HBASE_HOME}/conf</filename>, or</para>
            </step>

            <step>
              <para>if only a small set of HDFS client configurations, add them to
                  <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>.</para>
            </step>
          </stepalternatives>
        </step>
      </procedure>
      <para>An example of such an HDFS client configuration is <varname>dfs.replication</varname>.
        If for example, you want to run with a replication factor of 5, hbase will create files with
        the default of 3 unless you do the above to make the configuration available to
        HBase.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

    <section
      xml:id="confirm">
      <title>Running and Confirming Your Installation</title>



      <para>Make sure HDFS is running first. Start and stop the Hadoop HDFS daemons by running
          <filename>bin/start-hdfs.sh</filename> over in the <varname>HADOOP_HOME</varname>
        directory. You can ensure it started properly by testing the <command>put</command> and
          <command>get</command> of files into the Hadoop filesystem. HBase does not normally use
        the mapreduce daemons. These do not need to be started.</para>
      <para><emphasis>If</emphasis> you are managing your own ZooKeeper, start it and confirm its
        running else, HBase will start up ZooKeeper for you as part of its start process.</para>
      <para>Start HBase with the following command:</para>
      <screen>bin/start-hbase.sh</screen>
      <para>Run the above from the <varname>HBASE_HOME</varname> directory.</para>
      <para>You should now have a running HBase instance. HBase logs can be found in the
          <filename>logs</filename> subdirectory. Check them out especially if HBase had trouble
        starting.</para>

      <para>HBase also puts up a UI listing vital attributes. By default its deployed on the Master
        host at port 16010 (HBase RegionServers listen on port 16020 by default and put up an
        informational http server at 16030). If the Master were running on a host named
          <varname>master.example.org</varname> on the default port, to see the Master's homepage
        you'd point your browser at <filename>http://master.example.org:16010</filename>.</para>

      <para>Prior to HBase 0.98, the default ports the master ui was deployed on port 16010, and the
        HBase RegionServers would listen on port 16020 by default and put up an informational http
        server at 16030. </para>

      <para>Once HBase has started, see the <xref
          linkend="shell_exercises" /> for how to create tables, add data, scan your insertions, and
        finally disable and drop your tables.</para>

      <para>To stop HBase after exiting the HBase shell enter</para>
      <screen language="bourne">$ ./bin/stop-hbase.sh
stopping hbase...............</screen>
      <para>Shutdown can take a moment to complete. It can take longer if your cluster is comprised
        of many machines. If you are running a distributed operation, be sure to wait until HBase
        has shut down completely before stopping the Hadoop daemons.</para>
    </section>

  <!--  run modes -->



  <section
    xml:id="config.files">
    <title>Configuration Files</title>

    <section
      xml:id="hbase.site">
      <title><filename>hbase-site.xml</filename> and <filename>hbase-default.xml</filename></title>
      <para>Just as in Hadoop where you add site-specific HDFS configuration to the
          <filename>hdfs-site.xml</filename> file, for HBase, site specific customizations go into
        the file <filename>conf/hbase-site.xml</filename>. For the list of configurable properties,
        see <xref
          linkend="hbase_default_configurations" /> below or view the raw
          <filename>hbase-default.xml</filename> source file in the HBase source code at
          <filename>src/main/resources</filename>. </para>
      <para> Not all configuration options make it out to <filename>hbase-default.xml</filename>.
        Configuration that it is thought rare anyone would change can exist only in code; the only
        way to turn up such configurations is via a reading of the source code itself. </para>
      <para> Currently, changes here will require a cluster restart for HBase to notice the change. </para>
      <!--The file hbase-default.xml is generated as part of
    the build of the hbase site.  See the hbase pom.xml.
    The generated file is a docbook section with a glossary
    in it-->
      <!--presumes the pre-site target has put the hbase-default.xml at this location-->
      <xi:include
        xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        href="hbase-default.xml">
	<!--<xi:fallback>
          <section
            xml:id="hbase_default_configurations">
            <title />
            <para>
              <emphasis>This file is fallback content</emphasis>. If you are seeing this, something
              is wrong with the build of the HBase documentation or you are doing pre-build
              verification. </para>
            <para> The file hbase-default.xml is generated as part of the build of the hbase site.
              See the hbase <filename>pom.xml</filename>. The generated file is a docbook glossary. </para>
            <section>
              <title>IDs that are auto-generated and cause validation errors if not present</title>
              <para> Each of these is a reference to a configuration file parameter which will cause
                an error if you are using the fallback content here. This is a dirty dirty hack. </para>
              <section
                xml:id="fail.fast.expired.active.master">
                <title>fail.fast.expired.active.master</title>
                <para />
              </section>
              <section
                xml:id="hbase.hregion.memstore.flush.size">
                <title>"hbase.hregion.memstore.flush.size"</title>
                <para />
              </section>
              <section
                xml:id="hbase.hstore.bytes.per.checksum">
                <title>hbase.hstore.bytes.per.checksum</title>
                <para />
              </section>
              <section
                xml:id="hbase.online.schema.update.enable">
                <title>hbase.online.schema.update.enable</title>
                <para />
              </section>
              <section
                xml:id="hbase.regionserver.global.memstore.size">
                <title>hbase.regionserver.global.memstore.size</title>
                <para />
              </section>
              <section
                xml:id="hbase.hregion.max.filesize">
                <title>hbase.hregion.max.filesize</title>
                <para />
              </section>
              <section
                xml:id="hbase.hstore.blockingStoreFiles">
                <title>hbase.hstore.BlockingStoreFiles</title>
                <para />
              </section>
              <section
                xml:id="hfile.block.cache.size">
                <title>hfile.block.cache.size</title>
                <para />
              </section>
              <section
                xml:id="copy.table">
                <title>copy.table</title>
                <para />
              </section>
              <section
                xml:id="hbase.hstore.checksum.algorithm">
                <title>hbase.hstore.checksum.algorithm</title>
                <para />
              </section>
              <section
                xml:id="hbase.zookeeper.useMulti">
                <title>hbase.zookeeper.useMulti</title>
                <para />
              </section>
              <section
                xml:id="hbase.hregion.memstore.block.multiplier">
                <title>hbase.hregion.memstore.block.multiplier</title>
                <para />
              </section>
              <section
                xml:id="hbase.regionserver.global.memstore.size.lower.limit">
                <title>hbase.regionserver.global.memstore.size.lower.limit</title>
                <para />
              </section>
            </section>
          </section>
	</xi:fallback>-->
      </xi:include>
    </section>

    <section
      xml:id="hbase.env.sh">
      <title><filename>hbase-env.sh</filename></title>
      <para>Set HBase environment variables in this file. Examples include options to pass the JVM
        on start of an HBase daemon such as heap size and garbage collector configs. You can also
        set configurations for HBase configuration, log directories, niceness, ssh options, where to
        locate process pid files, etc. Open the file at <filename>conf/hbase-env.sh</filename> and
        peruse its content. Each option is fairly well documented. Add your own environment
        variables here if you want them read by HBase daemons on startup.</para>
      <para> Changes here will require a cluster restart for HBase to notice the change. </para>
    </section>

    <section
      xml:id="log4j">
      <title><filename>log4j.properties</filename></title>
      <para>Edit this file to change rate at which HBase files are rolled and to change the level at
        which HBase logs messages. </para>
      <para> Changes here will require a cluster restart for HBase to notice the change though log
        levels can be changed for particular daemons via the HBase UI. </para>
    </section>

    <section
      xml:id="client_dependencies">
      <title>Client configuration and dependencies connecting to an HBase cluster</title>
      <para>If you are running HBase in standalone mode, you don't need to configure anything for
        your client to work provided that they are all on the same machine.</para>
      <para> Since the HBase Master may move around, clients bootstrap by looking to ZooKeeper for
        current critical locations. ZooKeeper is where all these values are kept. Thus clients
        require the location of the ZooKeeper ensemble information before they can do anything else.
        Usually this the ensemble location is kept out in the <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>
        and is picked up by the client from the <varname>CLASSPATH</varname>.</para>

      <para>If you are configuring an IDE to run a HBase client, you should include the
          <filename>conf/</filename> directory on your classpath so
          <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename> settings can be found (or add
          <filename>src/test/resources</filename> to pick up the hbase-site.xml used by tests). </para>
      <para> Minimally, a client of HBase needs several libraries in its
          <varname>CLASSPATH</varname> when connecting to a cluster, including:
        <programlisting>
commons-configuration (commons-configuration-1.6.jar)
commons-lang (commons-lang-2.5.jar)
commons-logging (commons-logging-1.1.1.jar)
hadoop-core (hadoop-core-1.0.0.jar)
hbase (hbase-0.92.0.jar)
log4j (log4j-1.2.16.jar)
slf4j-api (slf4j-api-1.5.8.jar)
slf4j-log4j (slf4j-log4j12-1.5.8.jar)
zookeeper (zookeeper-3.4.2.jar)</programlisting>
      </para>
      <para> An example basic <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename> for client only might look as
        follows: <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="configuration.xsl"?>
<configuration>
  <property>
    <name>hbase.zookeeper.quorum</name>
    <value>example1,example2,example3</value>
    <description>The directory shared by region servers.
    </description>
  </property>
</configuration>
]]></programlisting>
      </para>

      <section
        xml:id="java.client.config">
        <title>Java client configuration</title>
        <para>The configuration used by a Java client is kept in an <link
            xlink:href="http://hbase.apache.org/apidocs/org/apache/hadoop/hbase/HBaseConfiguration">HBaseConfiguration</link>
          instance. The factory method on HBaseConfiguration,
            <code>HBaseConfiguration.create();</code>, on invocation, will read in the content of
          the first <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename> found on the client's
            <varname>CLASSPATH</varname>, if one is present (Invocation will also factor in any
            <filename>hbase-default.xml</filename> found; an hbase-default.xml ships inside the
            <filename>hbase.X.X.X.jar</filename>). It is also possible to specify configuration
          directly without having to read from a <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>. For example,
          to set the ZooKeeper ensemble for the cluster programmatically do as follows:
          <programlisting language="java">Configuration config = HBaseConfiguration.create();
config.set("hbase.zookeeper.quorum", "localhost");  // Here we are running zookeeper locally</programlisting>
          If multiple ZooKeeper instances make up your ZooKeeper ensemble, they may be specified in
          a comma-separated list (just as in the <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename> file). This
          populated <classname>Configuration</classname> instance can then be passed to an <link
            xlink:href="http://hbase.apache.org/apidocs/org/apache/hadoop/hbase/client/HTable.html">HTable</link>,
          and so on. </para>
      </section>
    </section>

  </section>
  <!--  config files -->

  <section
    xml:id="example_config">
    <title>Example Configurations</title>

    <section>
      <title>Basic Distributed HBase Install</title>

      <para>Here is an example basic configuration for a distributed ten node cluster. The nodes are
        named <varname>example0</varname>, <varname>example1</varname>, etc., through node
          <varname>example9</varname> in this example. The HBase Master and the HDFS namenode are
        running on the node <varname>example0</varname>. RegionServers run on nodes
          <varname>example1</varname>-<varname>example9</varname>. A 3-node ZooKeeper ensemble runs
        on <varname>example1</varname>, <varname>example2</varname>, and <varname>example3</varname>
        on the default ports. ZooKeeper data is persisted to the directory
          <filename>/export/zookeeper</filename>. Below we show what the main configuration files --
          <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>, <filename>regionservers</filename>, and
          <filename>hbase-env.sh</filename> -- found in the HBase <filename>conf</filename>
        directory might look like.</para>

      <section
        xml:id="hbase_site">
        <title><filename>hbase-site.xml</filename></title>

        <programlisting language="bourne">
<![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="configuration.xsl"?>
<configuration>
  <property>
    <name>hbase.zookeeper.quorum</name>
    <value>example1,example2,example3</value>
    <description>The directory shared by RegionServers.
    </description>
  </property>
  <property>
    <name>hbase.zookeeper.property.dataDir</name>
    <value>/export/zookeeper</value>
    <description>Property from ZooKeeper config zoo.cfg.
    The directory where the snapshot is stored.
    </description>
  </property>
  <property>
    <name>hbase.rootdir</name>
    <value>hdfs://example0:8020/hbase</value>
    <description>The directory shared by RegionServers.
    </description>
  </property>
  <property>
    <name>hbase.cluster.distributed</name>
    <value>true</value>
    <description>The mode the cluster will be in. Possible values are
      false: standalone and pseudo-distributed setups with managed Zookeeper
      true: fully-distributed with unmanaged Zookeeper Quorum (see hbase-env.sh)
    </description>
  </property>
</configuration>
]]>
        </programlisting>
      </section>

      <section
        xml:id="regionservers">
        <title><filename>regionservers</filename></title>

        <para>In this file you list the nodes that will run RegionServers. In our case, these nodes
          are <varname>example1</varname>-<varname>example9</varname>. </para>

        <programlisting>
example1
example2
example3
example4
example5
example6
example7
example8
example9
        </programlisting>
      </section>

      <section
        xml:id="hbase_env">
        <title><filename>hbase-env.sh</filename></title>

        <para>The following lines in the <filename>hbase-env.sh</filename> file show how to set the
            <envar>JAVA_HOME</envar> environment variable (required for HBase 0.98.5 and newer) and
          set the heap to 4 GB (rather than the default value of 1 GB). If you copy and paste this
          example, be sure to adjust the <envar>JAVA_HOME</envar> to suit your environment.</para>

        <screen language="bourne">
# The java implementation to use.
export JAVA_HOME=/usr/java/jdk1.7.0/          

# The maximum amount of heap to use, in MB. Default is 1000.
export HBASE_HEAPSIZE=4096
        </screen>

        <para>Use <command>rsync</command> to copy the content of the <filename>conf</filename>
          directory to all nodes of the cluster.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <!-- example config -->


  <section
    xml:id="important_configurations">
    <title>The Important Configurations</title>
    <para>Below we list what the <emphasis>important</emphasis> Configurations. We've divided this
      section into required configuration and worth-a-look recommended configs. </para>


    <section
      xml:id="required_configuration">
      <title>Required Configurations</title>
      <para>Review the <xref
          linkend="os" /> and <xref
          linkend="hadoop" /> sections. </para>
      <section
        xml:id="big.cluster.config">
        <title>Big Cluster Configurations</title>
        <para>If a cluster with a lot of regions, it is possible if an eager beaver regionserver
          checks in soon after master start while all the rest in the cluster are laggardly, this
          first server to checkin will be assigned all regions. If lots of regions, this first
          server could buckle under the load. To prevent the above scenario happening up the
            <varname>hbase.master.wait.on.regionservers.mintostart</varname> from its default value
          of 1. See <link
            xlink:href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HBASE-6389">HBASE-6389 Modify the
            conditions to ensure that Master waits for sufficient number of Region Servers before
            starting region assignments</link> for more detail. </para>
      </section>
      <section
        xml:id="backup.master.fail.fast">
        <title>If a backup Master, making primary Master fail fast</title>
        <para>If the primary Master loses its connection with ZooKeeper, it will fall into a loop
          where it keeps trying to reconnect. Disable this functionality if you are running more
          than one Master: i.e. a backup Master. Failing to do so, the dying Master may continue to
          receive RPCs though another Master has assumed the role of primary. See the configuration <xref
            linkend="fail.fast.expired.active.master" />. </para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section
      xml:id="recommended_configurations">
      <title>Recommended Configurations</title>
      <section
        xml:id="recommended_configurations.zk">
        <title>ZooKeeper Configuration</title>
        <section
          xml:id="sect.zookeeper.session.timeout">
          <title><varname>zookeeper.session.timeout</varname></title>
          <para>The default timeout is three minutes (specified in milliseconds). This means that if
            a server crashes, it will be three minutes before the Master notices the crash and
            starts recovery. You might like to tune the timeout down to a minute or even less so the
            Master notices failures the sooner. Before changing this value, be sure you have your
            JVM garbage collection configuration under control otherwise, a long garbage collection
            that lasts beyond the ZooKeeper session timeout will take out your RegionServer (You
            might be fine with this -- you probably want recovery to start on the server if a
            RegionServer has been in GC for a long period of time).</para>

          <para>To change this configuration, edit <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>, copy the
            changed file around the cluster and restart.</para>

          <para>We set this value high to save our having to field noob questions up on the mailing
            lists asking why a RegionServer went down during a massive import. The usual cause is
            that their JVM is untuned and they are running into long GC pauses. Our thinking is that
            while users are getting familiar with HBase, we'd save them having to know all of its
            intricacies. Later when they've built some confidence, then they can play with
            configuration such as this. </para>
        </section>
        <section
          xml:id="zookeeper.instances">
          <title>Number of ZooKeeper Instances</title>
          <para>See <xref
              linkend="zookeeper" />. </para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section
        xml:id="recommended.configurations.hdfs">
        <title>HDFS Configurations</title>
        <section
          xml:id="dfs.datanode.failed.volumes.tolerated">
          <title>dfs.datanode.failed.volumes.tolerated</title>
          <para>This is the "...number of volumes that are allowed to fail before a datanode stops
            offering service. By default any volume failure will cause a datanode to shutdown" from
            the <filename>hdfs-default.xml</filename> description. If you have > three or four
            disks, you might want to set this to 1 or if you have many disks, two or more. </para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section
        xml:id="hbase.regionserver.handler.count-description">
        <title><varname>hbase.regionserver.handler.count</varname></title>
        <para> This setting defines the number of threads that are kept open to answer incoming
          requests to user tables. The rule of thumb is to keep this number low when the payload per
          request approaches the MB (big puts, scans using a large cache) and high when the payload
          is small (gets, small puts, ICVs, deletes). The total size of the queries in progress is
          limited by the setting "hbase.ipc.server.max.callqueue.size". </para>
        <para> It is safe to set that number to the maximum number of incoming clients if their
          payload is small, the typical example being a cluster that serves a website since puts
          aren't typically buffered and most of the operations are gets. </para>
        <para> The reason why it is dangerous to keep this setting high is that the aggregate size
          of all the puts that are currently happening in a region server may impose too much
          pressure on its memory, or even trigger an OutOfMemoryError. A region server running on
          low memory will trigger its JVM's garbage collector to run more frequently up to a point
          where GC pauses become noticeable (the reason being that all the memory used to keep all
          the requests' payloads cannot be trashed, no matter how hard the garbage collector tries).
          After some time, the overall cluster throughput is affected since every request that hits
          that region server will take longer, which exacerbates the problem even more. </para>
        <para>You can get a sense of whether you have too little or too many handlers by <xref
            linkend="rpc.logging" /> on an individual RegionServer then tailing its logs (Queued
          requests consume memory). </para>
      </section>
      <section
        xml:id="big_memory">
        <title>Configuration for large memory machines</title>
        <para> HBase ships with a reasonable, conservative configuration that will work on nearly
          all machine types that people might want to test with. If you have larger machines --
          HBase has 8G and larger heap -- you might the following configuration options helpful.
          TODO. </para>

      </section>

      <section
        xml:id="config.compression">
        <title>Compression</title>
        <para>You should consider enabling ColumnFamily compression. There are several options that
          are near-frictionless and in most all cases boost performance by reducing the size of
          StoreFiles and thus reducing I/O. </para>
        <para>See <xref
            linkend="compression" /> for more information.</para>
      </section>
      <section
        xml:id="config.wals">
        <title>Configuring the size and number of WAL files</title>
        <para>HBase uses <xref
            linkend="wal" /> to recover the memstore data that has not been flushed to disk in case
          of an RS failure. These WAL files should be configured to be slightly smaller than HDFS
          block (by default, HDFS block is 64Mb and WAL file is ~60Mb).</para>
        <para>HBase also has a limit on number of WAL files, designed to ensure there's never too
          much data that needs to be replayed during recovery. This limit needs to be set according
          to memstore configuration, so that all the necessary data would fit. It is recommended to
          allocated enough WAL files to store at least that much data (when all memstores are close
          to full). For example, with 16Gb RS heap, default memstore settings (0.4), and default WAL
          file size (~60Mb), 16Gb*0.4/60, the starting point for WAL file count is ~109. However, as
          all memstores are not expected to be full all the time, less WAL files can be
          allocated.</para>
      </section>
      <section
        xml:id="disable.splitting">
        <title>Managed Splitting</title>
        <para>HBase generally handles splitting your regions, based upon the settings in your
            <filename>hbase-default.xml</filename> and <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>
          configuration files. Important settings include
            <varname>hbase.regionserver.region.split.policy</varname>,
            <varname>hbase.hregion.max.filesize</varname>,
            <varname>hbase.regionserver.regionSplitLimit</varname>. A simplistic view of splitting
          is that when a region grows to <varname>hbase.hregion.max.filesize</varname>, it is split.
          For most use patterns, most of the time, you should use automatic splitting. See <xref
            linkend="manual_region_splitting_decisions"/> for more information about manual region
          splitting.</para>
        <para>Instead of allowing HBase to split your regions automatically, you can choose to
          manage the splitting yourself. This feature was added in HBase 0.90.0. Manually managing
          splits works if you know your keyspace well, otherwise let HBase figure where to split for you.
          Manual splitting can mitigate region creation and movement under load. It also makes it so
          region boundaries are known and invariant (if you disable region splitting). If you use manual
          splits, it is easier doing staggered, time-based major compactions spread out your network IO
          load.</para>

        <formalpara>
          <title>Disable Automatic Splitting</title>
          <para>To disable automatic splitting, set <varname>hbase.hregion.max.filesize</varname> to
            a very large value, such as <literal>100 GB</literal> It is not recommended to set it to
            its absolute maximum value of <literal>Long.MAX_VALUE</literal>.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <note>
          <title>Automatic Splitting Is Recommended</title>
          <para>If you disable automatic splits to diagnose a problem or during a period of fast
            data growth, it is recommended to re-enable them when your situation becomes more
            stable. The potential benefits of managing region splits yourself are not
            undisputed.</para>
        </note>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Determine the Optimal Number of Pre-Split Regions</title>
          <para>The optimal number of pre-split regions depends on your application and environment.
            A good rule of thumb is to start with 10 pre-split regions per server and watch as data
            grows over time. It is better to err on the side of too few regions and perform rolling
            splits later. The optimal number of regions depends upon the largest StoreFile in your
            region. The size of the largest StoreFile will increase with time if the amount of data
            grows. The goal is for the largest region to be just large enough that the compaction
            selection algorithm only compacts it during a timed major compaction. Otherwise, the
            cluster can be prone to compaction storms where a large number of regions under
            compaction at the same time. It is important to understand that the data growth causes
            compaction storms, and not the manual split decision.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para>If the regions are split into too many large regions, you can increase the major
          compaction interval by configuring <varname>HConstants.MAJOR_COMPACTION_PERIOD</varname>.
          HBase 0.90 introduced <classname>org.apache.hadoop.hbase.util.RegionSplitter</classname>,
          which provides a network-IO-safe rolling split of all regions.</para>
      </section>
      <section
        xml:id="managed.compactions">
        <title>Managed Compactions</title>
        <para>By default, major compactions are scheduled to run once in a 7-day period. Prior to HBase 0.96.x, major
          compactions were scheduled to happen once per day by default.</para>
        <para>If you need to control exactly when and how often major compaction runs, you can
          disable managed major compactions. See the entry for
            <varname>hbase.hregion.majorcompaction</varname> in the <xref
            linkend="compaction.parameters" /> table for details.</para>
        <warning>
          <title>Do Not Disable Major Compactions</title>
          <para>Major compactions are absolutely necessary for StoreFile clean-up. Do not disable
            them altogether. You can run major compactions manually via the HBase shell or via the <link
              xlink:href="http://hbase.apache.org/apidocs/org/apache/hadoop/hbase/client/HBaseAdmin.html#majorCompact%28java.lang.String%29">HBaseAdmin
              API</link>.</para>
        </warning>        
        <para>For more information about compactions and the compaction file selection process, see <xref
            linkend="compaction" /></para>
      </section>

      <section
        xml:id="spec.ex">
        <title>Speculative Execution</title>
        <para>Speculative Execution of MapReduce tasks is on by default, and for HBase clusters it
          is generally advised to turn off Speculative Execution at a system-level unless you need
          it for a specific case, where it can be configured per-job. Set the properties
            <varname>mapreduce.map.speculative</varname> and
            <varname>mapreduce.reduce.speculative</varname> to false. </para>
      </section>
    </section>
      <section xml:id="other_configuration"><title>Other Configurations</title>
         <section xml:id="balancer_config"><title>Balancer</title>
           <para>The balancer is a periodic operation which is run on the master to redistribute regions on the cluster.  It is configured via
           <varname>hbase.balancer.period</varname> and defaults to 300000 (5 minutes). </para>
           <para>See <xref linkend="master.processes.loadbalancer" /> for more information on the LoadBalancer.
           </para>
         </section>
        <section xml:id="disabling.blockcache"><title>Disabling Blockcache</title>
          <para>Do not turn off block cache (You'd do it by setting <varname>hbase.block.cache.size</varname> to zero).
          Currently we do not do well if you do this because the regionserver will spend all its time loading hfile
          indices over and over again.  If your working set it such that block cache does you no good, at least
          size the block cache such that hfile indices will stay up in the cache (you can get a rough idea
          on the size you need by surveying regionserver UIs; you'll see index block size accounted near the
          top of the webpage).</para>
        </section>
    <section xml:id="nagles">
      <title><link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nagle's_algorithm">Nagle's</link> or the small package problem</title>
      <para>If a big 40ms or so occasional delay is seen in operations against HBase,
      try the Nagles' setting.  For example, see the user mailing list thread,
      <link xlink:href="http://search-hadoop.com/m/pduLg2fydtE/Inconsistent+scan+performance+with+caching+set+&amp;subj=Re+Inconsistent+scan+performance+with+caching+set+to+1">Inconsistent scan performance with caching set to 1</link>
      and the issue cited therein where setting notcpdelay improved scan speeds.  You might also
      see the graphs on the tail of <link xlink:href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HBASE-7008">HBASE-7008 Set scanner caching to a better default</link>
      where our Lars Hofhansl tries various data sizes w/ Nagle's on and off measuring the effect.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="mttr">
      <title>Better Mean Time to Recover (MTTR)</title>
      <para>This section is about configurations that will make servers come back faster after a fail.
          See the Deveraj Das an Nicolas Liochon blog post
          <link xlink:href="http://hortonworks.com/blog/introduction-to-hbase-mean-time-to-recover-mttr/">Introduction to HBase Mean Time to Recover (MTTR)</link>
          for a brief introduction.</para>
      <para>The issue <link xlink:href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HBASE-8389">HBASE-8354 forces Namenode into loop with lease recovery requests</link>
          is messy but has a bunch of good discussion toward the end on low timeouts and how to effect faster recovery including citation of fixes
          added to HDFS.  Read the Varun Sharma comments.  The below suggested configurations are Varun's suggestions distilled and tested.  Make sure you are
          running on a late-version HDFS so you have the fixes he refers too and himself adds to HDFS that help HBase MTTR
          (e.g. HDFS-3703, HDFS-3712, and HDFS-4791 -- hadoop 2 for sure has them and late hadoop 1 has some).
          Set the following in the RegionServer.</para>
      <programlisting language="xml">
<![CDATA[<property>
<property>
    <name>hbase.lease.recovery.dfs.timeout</name>
    <value>23000</value>
    <description>How much time we allow elapse between calls to recover lease.
    Should be larger than the dfs timeout.</description>
</property>
<property>
    <name>dfs.client.socket-timeout</name>
    <value>10000</value>
    <description>Down the DFS timeout from 60 to 10 seconds.</description>
</property>
]]></programlisting>

        <para>And on the namenode/datanode side, set the following to enable 'staleness' introduced
          in HDFS-3703, HDFS-3912. </para>
        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<property>
    <name>dfs.client.socket-timeout</name>
    <value>10000</value>
    <description>Down the DFS timeout from 60 to 10 seconds.</description>
</property>
<property>
    <name>dfs.datanode.socket.write.timeout</name>
    <value>10000</value>
    <description>Down the DFS timeout from 8 * 60 to 10 seconds.</description>
</property>
<property>
    <name>ipc.client.connect.timeout</name>
    <value>3000</value>
    <description>Down from 60 seconds to 3.</description>
</property>
<property>
    <name>ipc.client.connect.max.retries.on.timeouts</name>
    <value>2</value>
    <description>Down from 45 seconds to 3 (2 == 3 retries).</description>
</property>
<property>
    <name>dfs.namenode.avoid.read.stale.datanode</name>
    <value>true</value>
    <description>Enable stale state in hdfs</description>
</property>
<property>
    <name>dfs.namenode.stale.datanode.interval</name>
    <value>20000</value>
    <description>Down from default 30 seconds</description>
</property>
<property>
    <name>dfs.namenode.avoid.write.stale.datanode</name>
    <value>true</value>
    <description>Enable stale state in hdfs</description>
</property>
]]></programlisting>
      </section>

      <section
        xml:id="JMX_config">
        <title>JMX</title>
        <para>JMX(Java Management Extensions) provides built-in instrumentation that enables you
          to monitor and manage the Java VM. To enable monitoring and management from remote
          systems, you need to set system property com.sun.management.jmxremote.port(the port
          number through which you want to enable JMX RMI connections) when you start the Java VM.
          See <link
            xlink:href="http://docs.oracle.com/javase/6/docs/technotes/guides/management/agent.html">
          official document</link> for more information. Historically, besides above port mentioned,
          JMX opens 2 additional random TCP listening ports, which could lead to port conflict
          problem.(See <link
            xlink:href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HBASE-10289">HBASE-10289</link>
          for details)
        </para>
        <para>As an alternative, You can use the coprocessor-based JMX implementation provided
          by HBase. To enable it in 0.99 or above, add below property in
          <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>:
        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<property>
    <name>hbase.coprocessor.regionserver.classes</name>
    <value>org.apache.hadoop.hbase.JMXListener</value>
</property>
]]></programlisting>
          NOTE: DO NOT set com.sun.management.jmxremote.port for Java VM at the same time.
        </para>
        <para>Currently it supports Master and RegionServer Java VM. The reason why you only
          configure coprocessor for 'regionserver' is that, starting from HBase 0.99,
          a Master IS also a RegionServer. (See <link
            xlink:href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HBASE-10569">HBASE-10569</link>
          for more information.)
          By default, the JMX listens on TCP port 10102, you can further configure the port
          using below properties:

        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<property>
    <name>regionserver.rmi.registry.port</name>
    <value>61130</value>
</property>
<property>
    <name>regionserver.rmi.connector.port</name>
    <value>61140</value>
</property>
]]></programlisting>
          The registry port can be shared with connector port in most cases, so you only
          need to configure regionserver.rmi.registry.port. However if you want to use SSL
          communication, the 2 ports must be configured to different values.
        </para>

        <para>By default the password authentication and SSL communication is disabled.
          To enable password authentication, you need to update <filename>hbase-env.sh</filename>
          like below:
      <screen language="bourne">
export HBASE_JMX_BASE="-Dcom.sun.management.jmxremote.authenticate=true                  \
                       -Dcom.sun.management.jmxremote.password.file=your_password_file   \
                       -Dcom.sun.management.jmxremote.access.file=your_access_file"

export HBASE_MASTER_OPTS="$HBASE_MASTER_OPTS $HBASE_JMX_BASE "
export HBASE_REGIONSERVER_OPTS="$HBASE_REGIONSERVER_OPTS $HBASE_JMX_BASE "
      </screen>
          See example password/access file under $JRE_HOME/lib/management.
        </para>

        <para>To enable SSL communication with password authentication, follow below steps:
      <screen language="bourne">
#1. generate a key pair, stored in myKeyStore
keytool -genkey -alias jconsole -keystore myKeyStore

#2. export it to file jconsole.cert
keytool -export -alias jconsole -keystore myKeyStore -file jconsole.cert

#3. copy jconsole.cert to jconsole client machine, import it to jconsoleKeyStore
keytool -import -alias jconsole -keystore jconsoleKeyStore -file jconsole.cert
      </screen>
          And then update <filename>hbase-env.sh</filename> like below:
      <screen language="bourne">
export HBASE_JMX_BASE="-Dcom.sun.management.jmxremote.ssl=true                         \
                       -Djavax.net.ssl.keyStore=/home/tianq/myKeyStore                 \
                       -Djavax.net.ssl.keyStorePassword=your_password_in_step_1       \
                       -Dcom.sun.management.jmxremote.authenticate=true                \
                       -Dcom.sun.management.jmxremote.password.file=your_password file \
                       -Dcom.sun.management.jmxremote.access.file=your_access_file"

export HBASE_MASTER_OPTS="$HBASE_MASTER_OPTS $HBASE_JMX_BASE "
export HBASE_REGIONSERVER_OPTS="$HBASE_REGIONSERVER_OPTS $HBASE_JMX_BASE "
      </screen>

          Finally start jconsole on client using the key store:
      <screen language="bourne">
jconsole -J-Djavax.net.ssl.trustStore=/home/tianq/jconsoleKeyStore
      </screen>
        </para>
        <para>NOTE: for HBase 0.98, To enable the HBase JMX implementation on Master, you also
          need to add below property in <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>:
        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<property>
    <name>hbase.coprocessor.master.classes</name>
    <value>org.apache.hadoop.hbase.JMXListener</value>
</property>
]]></programlisting>
          The corresponding properties for port configuration are master.rmi.registry.port
          (by default 10101) and master.rmi.connector.port(by default the same as registry.port)
        </para>
    </section>

   </section>

  </section>
  <!--  important config -->
  <section xml:id="dyn_config">
    <title>Dynamic Configuration</title>
    <subtitle>Changing Configuration Without Restarting Servers</subtitle>
    <para>Since HBase 1.0.0, it is possible to change a subset of the configuration without
      requiring a server restart. In the hbase shell, there are new operators,
      <command>update_config</command> and <command>update_all_config</command> that
      will prompt a server or all servers to reload configuration.</para>
    <para>Only a subset of all configurations can currently be changed in the running server.
      Here is an incomplete list:
      <property>hbase.regionserver.thread.compaction.large</property>,
      <property>hbase.regionserver.thread.compaction.small</property>,
      <property>hbase.regionserver.thread.split</property>,
      <property>hbase.regionserver.thread.merge</property>, as well as compaction
      policy and configurations and adjustment to offpeak hours.
      For the full list consult the patch attached to 
      <link xlink:href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HBASE-12147">HBASE-12147 Porting Online Config Change from 89-fb</link>.
    </para>

  </section>
</chapter>
