<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="schema"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
  xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
  xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
  xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <!--
/**
 *
 * Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 * or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 * distributed with this work for additional information
 * regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 * to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 * "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 * with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 *
 *     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 *
 * Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 * distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 * WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 * See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 * limitations under the License.
 */
-->
  <title>HBase and Schema Design</title>
  <para>A good general introduction on the strength and weaknesses modelling on the various
    non-rdbms datastores is Ian Varley's Master thesis, <link
      xlink:href="http://ianvarley.com/UT/MR/Varley_MastersReport_Full_2009-08-07.pdf">No Relation:
      The Mixed Blessings of Non-Relational Databases</link>. Recommended. Also, read <xref
      linkend="keyvalue" /> for how HBase stores data internally, and the section on <xref
      linkend="schema.casestudies" />. </para>
  <section
    xml:id="schema.creation">
    <title> Schema Creation </title>
    <para>HBase schemas can be created or updated with <xref
        linkend="shell" /> or by using <link
        xlink:href="http://hbase.apache.org/apidocs/org/apache/hadoop/hbase/client/HBaseAdmin.html">HBaseAdmin</link>
      in the Java API. </para>
    <para>Tables must be disabled when making ColumnFamily modifications, for example:</para>
    <programlisting language="java">
Configuration config = HBaseConfiguration.create();
HBaseAdmin admin = new HBaseAdmin(conf);
String table = "myTable";

admin.disableTable(table);

HColumnDescriptor cf1 = ...;
admin.addColumn(table, cf1);      // adding new ColumnFamily
HColumnDescriptor cf2 = ...;
admin.modifyColumn(table, cf2);    // modifying existing ColumnFamily

admin.enableTable(table);
    </programlisting>
    <para>See <xref
        linkend="client_dependencies" /> for more information about configuring client
      connections.</para>
    <para>Note: online schema changes are supported in the 0.92.x codebase, but the 0.90.x codebase
      requires the table to be disabled. </para>
    <section
      xml:id="schema.updates">
      <title>Schema Updates</title>
      <para>When changes are made to either Tables or ColumnFamilies (e.g., region size, block
        size), these changes take effect the next time there is a major compaction and the
        StoreFiles get re-written. </para>
      <para>See <xref
          linkend="store" /> for more information on StoreFiles. </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section
    xml:id="number.of.cfs">
    <title> On the number of column families </title>
    <para> HBase currently does not do well with anything above two or three column families so keep
      the number of column families in your schema low. Currently, flushing and compactions are done
      on a per Region basis so if one column family is carrying the bulk of the data bringing on
      flushes, the adjacent families will also be flushed though the amount of data they carry is
      small. When many column families the flushing and compaction interaction can make for a bunch
      of needless i/o loading (To be addressed by changing flushing and compaction to work on a per
      column family basis). For more information on compactions, see <xref
        linkend="compaction" />. </para>
    <para>Try to make do with one column family if you can in your schemas. Only introduce a second
      and third column family in the case where data access is usually column scoped; i.e. you query
      one column family or the other but usually not both at the one time. </para>
    <section
      xml:id="number.of.cfs.card">
      <title>Cardinality of ColumnFamilies</title>
      <para>Where multiple ColumnFamilies exist in a single table, be aware of the cardinality
        (i.e., number of rows). If ColumnFamilyA has 1 million rows and ColumnFamilyB has 1 billion
        rows, ColumnFamilyA's data will likely be spread across many, many regions (and
        RegionServers). This makes mass scans for ColumnFamilyA less efficient. </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section
    xml:id="rowkey.design">
    <title>Rowkey Design</title>
    <section>
      <title>Hotspotting</title>
      <para>Rows in HBase are sorted lexicographically by row key. This design optimizes for scans,
        allowing you to store related rows, or rows that will be read together, near each other.
        However, poorly designed row keys are a common source of <firstterm>hotspotting</firstterm>.
        Hotspotting occurs when a large amount of client traffic is directed at one node, or only a
        few nodes, of a cluster. This traffic may represent reads, writes, or other operations. The
        traffic overwhelms the single machine responsible for hosting that region, causing
        performance degradation and potentially leading to region unavailability. This can also have
        adverse effects on other regions hosted by the same region server as that host is unable to
        service the requested load. It is important to design data access patterns such that the
        cluster is fully and evenly utilized.</para>
      <para>To prevent hotspotting on writes, design your row keys such that rows that truly do need
        to be in the same region are, but in the bigger picture, data is being written to multiple
        regions across the cluster, rather than one at a time. Some common techniques for avoiding
        hotspotting are described below, along with some of their advantages and drawbacks.</para>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Salting</title>
        <para>Salting in this sense has nothing to do with cryptography, but refers to adding random
          data to the start of a row key. In this case, salting refers to adding a randomly-assigned
          prefix to the row key to cause it to sort differently than it otherwise would. The number
          of possible prefixes correspond to the number of regions you want to spread the data
          across. Salting can be helpful if you have a few "hot" row key patterns which come up over
          and over amongst other more evenly-distributed rows. Consider the following example, which
          shows that salting can spread write load across multiple regionservers, and illustrates
          some of the negative implications for reads.</para>
      </formalpara>
      <example>
        <title>Salting Example</title>
        <para>Suppose you have the following list of row keys, and your table is split such that
          there is one region for each letter of the alphabet. Prefix 'a' is one region, prefix 'b'
          is another. In this table, all rows starting with 'f' are in the same region. This example
          focuses on rows with keys like the following:</para>
        <screen>
foo0001
foo0002
foo0003
foo0004          
        </screen>
        <para>Now, imagine that you would like to spread these across four different regions. You
          decide to use four different salts: <literal>a</literal>, <literal>b</literal>,
            <literal>c</literal>, and <literal>d</literal>. In this scenario, each of these letter
          prefixes will be on a different region. After applying the salts, you have the following
          rowkeys instead. Since you can now write to four separate regions, you theoretically have
          four times the throughput when writing that you would have if all the writes were going to
          the same region.</para>
        <screen>
a-foo0003
b-foo0001
c-foo0004
d-foo0002          
        </screen>
        <para>Then, if you add another row, it will randomly be assigned one of the four possible
          salt values and end up near one of the existing rows.</para>
        <screen>
a-foo0003
b-foo0001
<emphasis>c-foo0003</emphasis>
c-foo0004
d-foo0002        
        </screen>
        <para>Since this assignment will be random, you will need to do more work if you want to
          retrieve the rows in lexicographic order. In this way, salting attempts to increase
          throughput on writes, but has a cost during reads.</para>
      </example>
      <para></para>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Hashing</title>
        <para>Instead of a random assignment, you could use a one-way <firstterm>hash</firstterm>
          that would cause a given row to always be "salted" with the same prefix, in a way that
          would spread the load across the regionservers, but allow for predictability during reads.
          Using a deterministic hash allows the client to reconstruct the complete rowkey and use a
          Get operation to retrieve that row as normal.</para>
      </formalpara>
      <example>
        <title>Hashing Example</title>
        <para>Given the same situation in the salting example above, you could instead apply a
          one-way hash that would cause the row with key <literal>foo0003</literal> to always, and
          predictably, receive the <literal>a</literal> prefix. Then, to retrieve that row, you
          would already know the key. You could also optimize things so that certain pairs of keys
          were always in the same region, for instance.</para>
      </example>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Reversing the Key</title>
        <para>A third common trick for preventing hotspotting is to reverse a fixed-width or numeric
        row key so that the part that changes the most often (the least significant digit) is first.
        This effectively randomizes row keys, but sacrifices row ordering properties.</para>
      </formalpara>
      <para>See <link
          xlink:href="https://communities.intel.com/community/itpeernetwork/datastack/blog/2013/11/10/discussion-on-designing-hbase-tables"
          >https://communities.intel.com/community/itpeernetwork/datastack/blog/2013/11/10/discussion-on-designing-hbase-tables</link>,
        and <link xlink:href="http://phoenix.apache.org/salted.html">article on Salted Tables</link>
        from the Phoenix project, and the discussion in the comments of <link
          xlink:href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HBASE-11682">HBASE-11682</link> for more
        information about avoiding hotspotting.</para>
    </section>
    <section
      xml:id="timeseries">
      <title> Monotonically Increasing Row Keys/Timeseries Data </title>
      <para> In the HBase chapter of Tom White's book <link
          xlink:href="http://oreilly.com/catalog/9780596521981">Hadoop: The Definitive Guide</link>
        (O'Reilly) there is a an optimization note on watching out for a phenomenon where an import
        process walks in lock-step with all clients in concert pounding one of the table's regions
        (and thus, a single node), then moving onto the next region, etc. With monotonically
        increasing row-keys (i.e., using a timestamp), this will happen. See this comic by IKai Lan
        on why monotonically increasing row keys are problematic in BigTable-like datastores: <link
          xlink:href="http://ikaisays.com/2011/01/25/app-engine-datastore-tip-monotonically-increasing-values-are-bad/">monotonically
          increasing values are bad</link>. The pile-up on a single region brought on by
        monotonically increasing keys can be mitigated by randomizing the input records to not be in
        sorted order, but in general it's best to avoid using a timestamp or a sequence (e.g. 1, 2,
        3) as the row-key. </para>
      <para>If you do need to upload time series data into HBase, you should study <link
          xlink:href="http://opentsdb.net/">OpenTSDB</link> as a successful example. It has a page
        describing the <link
          xlink:href=" http://opentsdb.net/schema.html">schema</link> it uses in HBase. The key
        format in OpenTSDB is effectively [metric_type][event_timestamp], which would appear at
        first glance to contradict the previous advice about not using a timestamp as the key.
        However, the difference is that the timestamp is not in the <emphasis>lead</emphasis>
        position of the key, and the design assumption is that there are dozens or hundreds (or
        more) of different metric types. Thus, even with a continual stream of input data with a mix
        of metric types, the Puts are distributed across various points of regions in the table. </para>
      <para>See <xref
          linkend="schema.casestudies" /> for some rowkey design examples. </para>
    </section>
    <section
      xml:id="keysize">
      <title>Try to minimize row and column sizes</title>
      <subtitle>Or why are my StoreFile indices large?</subtitle>
      <para>In HBase, values are always freighted with their coordinates; as a cell value passes
        through the system, it'll be accompanied by its row, column name, and timestamp - always. If
        your rows and column names are large, especially compared to the size of the cell value,
        then you may run up against some interesting scenarios. One such is the case described by
        Marc Limotte at the tail of <link
          xlink:href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HBASE-3551?page=com.atlassian.jira.plugin.system.issuetabpanels:comment-tabpanel&amp;focusedCommentId=13005272#comment-13005272">HBASE-3551</link>
        (recommended!). Therein, the indices that are kept on HBase storefiles (<xref
          linkend="hfile" />) to facilitate random access may end up occupyng large chunks of the
        HBase allotted RAM because the cell value coordinates are large. Mark in the above cited
        comment suggests upping the block size so entries in the store file index happen at a larger
        interval or modify the table schema so it makes for smaller rows and column names.
        Compression will also make for larger indices. See the thread <link
          xlink:href="http://search-hadoop.com/m/hemBv1LiN4Q1/a+question+storefileIndexSize&amp;subj=a+question+storefileIndexSize">a
          question storefileIndexSize</link> up on the user mailing list. </para>
      <para>Most of the time small inefficiencies don't matter all that much. Unfortunately, this is
        a case where they do. Whatever patterns are selected for ColumnFamilies, attributes, and
        rowkeys they could be repeated several billion times in your data. </para>
      <para>See <xref
          linkend="keyvalue" /> for more information on HBase stores data internally to see why this
        is important.</para>
      <section
        xml:id="keysize.cf">
        <title>Column Families</title>
        <para>Try to keep the ColumnFamily names as small as possible, preferably one character
          (e.g. "d" for data/default). </para>
        <para>See <xref
            linkend="keyvalue" /> for more information on HBase stores data internally to see why
          this is important.</para>
      </section>
      <section
        xml:id="keysize.attributes">
        <title>Attributes</title>
        <para>Although verbose attribute names (e.g., "myVeryImportantAttribute") are easier to
          read, prefer shorter attribute names (e.g., "via") to store in HBase. </para>
        <para>See <xref
            linkend="keyvalue" /> for more information on HBase stores data internally to see why
          this is important.</para>
      </section>
      <section
        xml:id="keysize.row">
        <title>Rowkey Length</title>
        <para>Keep them as short as is reasonable such that they can still be useful for required
          data access (e.g., Get vs. Scan). A short key that is useless for data access is not
          better than a longer key with better get/scan properties. Expect tradeoffs when designing
          rowkeys. </para>
      </section>
      <section
        xml:id="keysize.patterns">
        <title>Byte Patterns</title>
        <para>A long is 8 bytes. You can store an unsigned number up to 18,446,744,073,709,551,615
          in those eight bytes. If you stored this number as a String -- presuming a byte per
          character -- you need nearly 3x the bytes. </para>
        <para>Not convinced? Below is some sample code that you can run on your own.</para>
        <programlisting language="java">
// long
//
long l = 1234567890L;
byte[] lb = Bytes.toBytes(l);
System.out.println("long bytes length: " + lb.length);   // returns 8

String s = "" + l;
byte[] sb = Bytes.toBytes(s);
System.out.println("long as string length: " + sb.length);    // returns 10

// hash
//
MessageDigest md = MessageDigest.getInstance("MD5");
byte[] digest = md.digest(Bytes.toBytes(s));
System.out.println("md5 digest bytes length: " + digest.length);    // returns 16

String sDigest = new String(digest);
byte[] sbDigest = Bytes.toBytes(sDigest);
System.out.println("md5 digest as string length: " + sbDigest.length);    // returns 26
        </programlisting>
        <para>Unfortunately, using a binary representation of a type will make your data harder to
          read outside of your code. For example, this is what you will see in the shell when you
          increment a value:</para>
        <programlisting>
hbase(main):001:0> incr 't', 'r', 'f:q', 1
COUNTER VALUE = 1

hbase(main):002:0> get 't', 'r'
COLUMN                                        CELL
 f:q                                          timestamp=1369163040570, value=\x00\x00\x00\x00\x00\x00\x00\x01
1 row(s) in 0.0310 seconds
        </programlisting>
        <para>The shell makes a best effort to print a string, and it this case it decided to just
          print the hex. The same will happen to your row keys inside the region names. It can be
          okay if you know what's being stored, but it might also be unreadable if arbitrary data
          can be put in the same cells. This is the main trade-off. </para>
      </section>

    </section>
    <section
      xml:id="reverse.timestamp">
      <title>Reverse Timestamps</title>
      <note>
        <title>Reverse Scan API</title>
        <para>
          <link
            xlink:href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HBASE-4811">HBASE-4811</link>
          implements an API to scan a table or a range within a table in reverse, reducing the need
          to optimize your schema for forward or reverse scanning. This feature is available in
          HBase 0.98 and later. See <link
            xlink:href="https://hbase.apache.org/apidocs/org/apache/hadoop/hbase/client/Scan.html#setReversed%28boolean" />
          for more information. </para>
      </note>

      <para>A common problem in database processing is quickly finding the most recent version of a
        value. A technique using reverse timestamps as a part of the key can help greatly with a
        special case of this problem. Also found in the HBase chapter of Tom White's book Hadoop:
        The Definitive Guide (O'Reilly), the technique involves appending (<code>Long.MAX_VALUE -
          timestamp</code>) to the end of any key, e.g., [key][reverse_timestamp]. </para>
      <para>The most recent value for [key] in a table can be found by performing a Scan for [key]
        and obtaining the first record. Since HBase keys are in sorted order, this key sorts before
        any older row-keys for [key] and thus is first. </para>
      <para>This technique would be used instead of using <xref
          linkend="schema.versions" /> where the intent is to hold onto all versions "forever" (or a
        very long time) and at the same time quickly obtain access to any other version by using the
        same Scan technique. </para>
    </section>
    <section
      xml:id="rowkey.scope">
      <title>Rowkeys and ColumnFamilies</title>
      <para>Rowkeys are scoped to ColumnFamilies. Thus, the same rowkey could exist in each
        ColumnFamily that exists in a table without collision. </para>
    </section>
    <section
      xml:id="changing.rowkeys">
      <title>Immutability of Rowkeys</title>
      <para>Rowkeys cannot be changed. The only way they can be "changed" in a table is if the row
        is deleted and then re-inserted. This is a fairly common question on the HBase dist-list so
        it pays to get the rowkeys right the first time (and/or before you've inserted a lot of
        data). </para>
    </section>
    <section
      xml:id="rowkey.regionsplits">
      <title>Relationship Between RowKeys and Region Splits</title>
      <para>If you pre-split your table, it is <emphasis>critical</emphasis> to understand how your
        rowkey will be distributed across the region boundaries. As an example of why this is
        important, consider the example of using displayable hex characters as the lead position of
        the key (e.g., "0000000000000000" to "ffffffffffffffff"). Running those key ranges through
          <code>Bytes.split</code> (which is the split strategy used when creating regions in
          <code>HBaseAdmin.createTable(byte[] startKey, byte[] endKey, numRegions)</code> for 10
        regions will generate the following splits...</para>
      <screen>
48 48 48 48 48 48 48 48 48 48 48 48 48 48 48 48                                // 0
54 -10 -10 -10 -10 -10 -10 -10 -10 -10 -10 -10 -10 -10 -10 -10                 // 6
61 -67 -67 -67 -67 -67 -67 -67 -67 -67 -67 -67 -67 -67 -67 -68                 // =
68 -124 -124 -124 -124 -124 -124 -124 -124 -124 -124 -124 -124 -124 -124 -126  // D
75 75 75 75 75 75 75 75 75 75 75 75 75 75 75 72                                // K
82 18 18 18 18 18 18 18 18 18 18 18 18 18 18 14                                // R
88 -40 -40 -40 -40 -40 -40 -40 -40 -40 -40 -40 -40 -40 -40 -44                 // X
95 -97 -97 -97 -97 -97 -97 -97 -97 -97 -97 -97 -97 -97 -97 -102                // _
102 102 102 102 102 102 102 102 102 102 102 102 102 102 102 102                // f
      </screen>
      <para>... (note: the lead byte is listed to the right as a comment.) Given that the first
        split is a '0' and the last split is an 'f', everything is great, right? Not so fast. </para>
      <para>The problem is that all the data is going to pile up in the first 2 regions and the last
        region thus creating a "lumpy" (and possibly "hot") region problem. To understand why, refer
        to an <link
          xlink:href="http://www.asciitable.com">ASCII Table</link>. '0' is byte 48, and 'f' is byte
        102, but there is a huge gap in byte values (bytes 58 to 96) that will <emphasis>never
          appear in this keyspace</emphasis> because the only values are [0-9] and [a-f]. Thus, the
        middle regions regions will never be used. To make pre-spliting work with this example
        keyspace, a custom definition of splits (i.e., and not relying on the built-in split method)
        is required. </para>
      <para>Lesson #1: Pre-splitting tables is generally a best practice, but you need to pre-split
        them in such a way that all the regions are accessible in the keyspace. While this example
        demonstrated the problem with a hex-key keyspace, the same problem can happen with
          <emphasis>any</emphasis> keyspace. Know your data. </para>
      <para>Lesson #2: While generally not advisable, using hex-keys (and more generally,
        displayable data) can still work with pre-split tables as long as all the created regions
        are accessible in the keyspace. </para>
      <para>To conclude this example, the following is an example of how appropriate splits can be
        pre-created for hex-keys:. </para>
      <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public static boolean createTable(HBaseAdmin admin, HTableDescriptor table, byte[][] splits)
throws IOException {
  try {
    admin.createTable( table, splits );
    return true;
  } catch (TableExistsException e) {
    logger.info("table " + table.getNameAsString() + " already exists");
    // the table already exists...
    return false;
  }
}

public static byte[][] getHexSplits(String startKey, String endKey, int numRegions) {
  byte[][] splits = new byte[numRegions-1][];
  BigInteger lowestKey = new BigInteger(startKey, 16);
  BigInteger highestKey = new BigInteger(endKey, 16);
  BigInteger range = highestKey.subtract(lowestKey);
  BigInteger regionIncrement = range.divide(BigInteger.valueOf(numRegions));
  lowestKey = lowestKey.add(regionIncrement);
  for(int i=0; i < numRegions-1;i++) {
    BigInteger key = lowestKey.add(regionIncrement.multiply(BigInteger.valueOf(i)));
    byte[] b = String.format("%016x", key).getBytes();
    splits[i] = b;
  }
  return splits;
}]]></programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>
  <!--  rowkey design -->
  <section
    xml:id="schema.versions">
    <title> Number of Versions </title>
    <section
      xml:id="schema.versions.max">
      <title>Maximum Number of Versions</title>
      <para>The maximum number of row versions to store is configured per column family via <link
          xlink:href="http://hbase.apache.org/apidocs/org/apache/hadoop/hbase/HColumnDescriptor.html">HColumnDescriptor</link>.
        The default for max versions is 1. This is an important parameter because as described in <xref
          linkend="datamodel" /> section HBase does <emphasis>not</emphasis> overwrite row values,
        but rather stores different values per row by time (and qualifier). Excess versions are
        removed during major compactions. The number of max versions may need to be increased or
        decreased depending on application needs. </para>
      <para>It is not recommended setting the number of max versions to an exceedingly high level
        (e.g., hundreds or more) unless those old values are very dear to you because this will
        greatly increase StoreFile size. </para>
    </section>
    <section
      xml:id="schema.minversions">
      <title> Minimum Number of Versions </title>
      <para>Like maximum number of row versions, the minimum number of row versions to keep is
        configured per column family via <link
          xlink:href="http://hbase.apache.org/apidocs/org/apache/hadoop/hbase/HColumnDescriptor.html">HColumnDescriptor</link>.
        The default for min versions is 0, which means the feature is disabled. The minimum number
        of row versions parameter is used together with the time-to-live parameter and can be
        combined with the number of row versions parameter to allow configurations such as "keep the
        last T minutes worth of data, at most N versions, <emphasis>but keep at least M versions
          around</emphasis>" (where M is the value for minimum number of row versions, M&lt;N). This
        parameter should only be set when time-to-live is enabled for a column family and must be
        less than the number of row versions. </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section
    xml:id="supported.datatypes">
    <title> Supported Datatypes </title>
    <para>HBase supports a "bytes-in/bytes-out" interface via <link
        xlink:href="http://hbase.apache.org/apidocs/org/apache/hadoop/hbase/client/Put.html">Put</link>
      and <link
        xlink:href="http://hbase.apache.org/apidocs/org/apache/hadoop/hbase/client/Result.html">Result</link>,
      so anything that can be converted to an array of bytes can be stored as a value. Input could
      be strings, numbers, complex objects, or even images as long as they can rendered as bytes. </para>
    <para>There are practical limits to the size of values (e.g., storing 10-50MB objects in HBase
      would probably be too much to ask); search the mailling list for conversations on this topic.
      All rows in HBase conform to the <xref
        linkend="datamodel" />, and that includes versioning. Take that into consideration when
      making your design, as well as block size for the ColumnFamily. </para>

    <section
      xml:id="counters">
      <title>Counters</title>
      <para> One supported datatype that deserves special mention are "counters" (i.e., the ability
        to do atomic increments of numbers). See <link
          xlink:href="http://hbase.apache.org/apidocs/org/apache/hadoop/hbase/client/HTable.html#increment%28org.apache.hadoop.hbase.client.Increment%29">Increment</link>
        in HTable. </para>
      <para>Synchronization on counters are done on the RegionServer, not in the client. </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section
    xml:id="schema.joins">
    <title>Joins</title>
    <para>If you have multiple tables, don't forget to factor in the potential for <xref
        linkend="joins" /> into the schema design. </para>
  </section>
  <section
    xml:id="ttl">
    <title>Time To Live (TTL)</title>
    <para> ColumnFamilies can set a TTL length in seconds, and HBase will automatically delete rows
      once the expiration time is reached. This applies to <emphasis>all</emphasis> versions of a
      row - even the current one. The TTL time encoded in the HBase for the row is specified in UTC.
    </para>
    <para> Store files which contains only expired rows are deleted on minor compaction. Setting
        <varname>hbase.store.delete.expired.storefile</varname> to <code>false</code> disables this
      feature. Setting <link linkend="schema.minversions">minimum number of versions</link> to other
      than 0 also disables this.</para>
    <para> See <link
        xlink:href="http://hbase.apache.org/apidocs/org/apache/hadoop/hbase/HColumnDescriptor.html"
        >HColumnDescriptor</link> for more information. </para>
    <para>Recent versions of HBase also support setting time to live on a per cell basis. See <link
        xlink:href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HBASE-10560">HBASE-10560</link> for more
        information. Cell TTLs are submitted as an attribute on mutation requests (Appends,
        Increments, Puts, etc.) using Mutation#setTTL. If the TTL attribute is set, it will be applied
        to all cells updated on the server by the operation. There are two notable differences
        between cell TTL handling and ColumnFamily TTLs:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Cell TTLs are expressed in units of milliseconds instead of seconds.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>A cell TTLs cannot extend the effective lifetime of a cell beyond a ColumnFamily level
          TTL setting.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section
    xml:id="cf.keep.deleted">
    <title> Keeping Deleted Cells </title>
    <para>By default, delete markers extend back to the beginning of time. Therefore, <link
        xlink:href="http://hbase.apache.org/apidocs/org/apache/hadoop/hbase/client/Get.html">Get</link>
      or <link
        xlink:href="http://hbase.apache.org/apidocs/org/apache/hadoop/hbase/client/Scan.html">Scan</link>
      operations will not see a deleted cell (row or column), even when the Get or Scan operation
      indicates a time range
      before the delete marker was placed.</para> 
    <para>ColumnFamilies can optionally keep deleted cells. In this case, deleted cells can still be
      retrieved, as long as these operations specify a time range that ends before the timestamp of
      any delete that would affect the cells. This allows for point-in-time queries even in the
      presence of deletes. </para>
    <para> Deleted cells are still subject to TTL and there will never be more than "maximum number
      of versions" deleted cells. A new "raw" scan options returns all deleted rows and the delete
      markers. </para>
    <example>
      <title>Change the Value of <code>KEEP_DELETED_CELLS</code> Using HBase Shell</title>
      <screen>hbase> hbase> alter ‘t1′, NAME => ‘f1′, KEEP_DELETED_CELLS => true</screen>
    </example>
    <example>
      <title>Change the Value of <code>KEEP_DELETED_CELLS</code> Using the API</title>
      <programlisting language="java">...
HColumnDescriptor.setKeepDeletedCells(true);
...
      </programlisting>
    </example>
    <para>See the API documentation for <link
        xlink:href="http://hbase.apache.org/apidocs/org/apache/hadoop/hbase/HColumnDescriptor.html#KEEP_DELETED_CELLS"
        >KEEP_DELETED_CELLS</link> for more information. </para>
  </section>
  <section
    xml:id="secondary.indexes">
    <title> Secondary Indexes and Alternate Query Paths </title>
    <para>This section could also be titled "what if my table rowkey looks like
        <emphasis>this</emphasis> but I also want to query my table like <emphasis>that</emphasis>."
      A common example on the dist-list is where a row-key is of the format "user-timestamp" but
      there are reporting requirements on activity across users for certain time ranges. Thus,
      selecting by user is easy because it is in the lead position of the key, but time is not. </para>
    <para>There is no single answer on the best way to handle this because it depends on... </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Number of users</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Data size and data arrival rate</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Flexibility of reporting requirements (e.g., completely ad-hoc date selection vs.
          pre-configured ranges) </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Desired execution speed of query (e.g., 90 seconds may be reasonable to some for an
          ad-hoc report, whereas it may be too long for others) </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>... and solutions are also influenced by the size of the cluster and how much processing
      power you have to throw at the solution. Common techniques are in sub-sections below. This is
      a comprehensive, but not exhaustive, list of approaches. </para>
    <para>It should not be a surprise that secondary indexes require additional cluster space and
      processing. This is precisely what happens in an RDBMS because the act of creating an
      alternate index requires both space and processing cycles to update. RDBMS products are more
      advanced in this regard to handle alternative index management out of the box. However, HBase
      scales better at larger data volumes, so this is a feature trade-off. </para>
    <para>Pay attention to <xref
        linkend="performance" /> when implementing any of these approaches.</para>
    <para>Additionally, see the David Butler response in this dist-list thread <link
        xlink:href="http://search-hadoop.com/m/nvbiBp2TDP/Stargate%252Bhbase&amp;subj=Stargate+hbase">HBase,
        mail # user - Stargate+hbase</link>
    </para>
    <section
      xml:id="secondary.indexes.filter">
      <title> Filter Query </title>
      <para>Depending on the case, it may be appropriate to use <xref
          linkend="client.filter" />. In this case, no secondary index is created. However, don't
        try a full-scan on a large table like this from an application (i.e., single-threaded
        client). </para>
    </section>
    <section
      xml:id="secondary.indexes.periodic">
      <title> Periodic-Update Secondary Index </title>
      <para>A secondary index could be created in an other table which is periodically updated via a
        MapReduce job. The job could be executed intra-day, but depending on load-strategy it could
        still potentially be out of sync with the main data table.</para>
      <para>See <xref
          linkend="mapreduce.example.readwrite" /> for more information.</para>
    </section>
    <section
      xml:id="secondary.indexes.dualwrite">
      <title> Dual-Write Secondary Index </title>
      <para>Another strategy is to build the secondary index while publishing data to the cluster
        (e.g., write to data table, write to index table). If this is approach is taken after a data
        table already exists, then bootstrapping will be needed for the secondary index with a
        MapReduce job (see <xref
          linkend="secondary.indexes.periodic" />).</para>
    </section>
    <section
      xml:id="secondary.indexes.summary">
      <title> Summary Tables </title>
      <para>Where time-ranges are very wide (e.g., year-long report) and where the data is
        voluminous, summary tables are a common approach. These would be generated with MapReduce
        jobs into another table.</para>
      <para>See <xref
          linkend="mapreduce.example.summary" /> for more information.</para>
    </section>
    <section
      xml:id="secondary.indexes.coproc">
      <title> Coprocessor Secondary Index </title>
      <para>Coprocessors act like RDBMS triggers. These were added in 0.92. For more information,
        see <xref
          linkend="coprocessors" />
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section
    xml:id="constraints">
    <title>Constraints</title>
    <para>HBase currently supports 'constraints' in traditional (SQL) database parlance. The advised
      usage for Constraints is in enforcing business rules for attributes in the table (eg. make
      sure values are in the range 1-10). Constraints could also be used to enforce referential
      integrity, but this is strongly discouraged as it will dramatically decrease the write
      throughput of the tables where integrity checking is enabled. Extensive documentation on using
      Constraints can be found at: <link
        xlink:href="http://hbase.apache.org/apidocs/org/apache/hadoop/hbase/constraint">Constraint</link>
      since version 0.94. </para>
  </section>
  <section
    xml:id="schema.casestudies">
    <title>Schema Design Case Studies</title>
    <para>The following will describe some typical data ingestion use-cases with HBase, and how the
      rowkey design and construction can be approached. Note: this is just an illustration of
      potential approaches, not an exhaustive list. Know your data, and know your processing
      requirements. </para>
    <para>It is highly recommended that you read the rest of the <xref
        linkend="schema" /> first, before reading these case studies. </para>
    <para>The following case studies are described: </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Log Data / Timeseries Data</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Log Data / Timeseries on Steroids</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Customer/Order</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Tall/Wide/Middle Schema Design</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>List Data</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <section
      xml:id="schema.casestudies.log-timeseries">
      <title>Case Study - Log Data and Timeseries Data</title>
      <para>Assume that the following data elements are being collected. </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Hostname</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Timestamp</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Log event</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Value/message</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>We can store them in an HBase table called LOG_DATA, but what will the rowkey be? From
        these attributes the rowkey will be some combination of hostname, timestamp, and log-event -
        but what specifically? </para>
      <section
        xml:id="schema.casestudies.log-timeseries.tslead">
        <title>Timestamp In The Rowkey Lead Position</title>
        <para>The rowkey <code>[timestamp][hostname][log-event]</code> suffers from the
          monotonically increasing rowkey problem described in <xref
            linkend="timeseries" />. </para>
        <para>There is another pattern frequently mentioned in the dist-lists about “bucketing”
          timestamps, by performing a mod operation on the timestamp. If time-oriented scans are
          important, this could be a useful approach. Attention must be paid to the number of
          buckets, because this will require the same number of scans to return results.</para>
        <programlisting language="java">
long bucket = timestamp % numBuckets;
        </programlisting>
        <para>… to construct:</para>
        <programlisting>
[bucket][timestamp][hostname][log-event]
        </programlisting>
        <para>As stated above, to select data for a particular timerange, a Scan will need to be
          performed for each bucket. 100 buckets, for example, will provide a wide distribution in
          the keyspace but it will require 100 Scans to obtain data for a single timestamp, so there
          are trade-offs. </para>
      </section>
      <!-- ts lead -->
      <section
        xml:id="schema.casestudies.log-timeseries.hostlead">
        <title>Host In The Rowkey Lead Position</title>
        <para>The rowkey <code>[hostname][log-event][timestamp]</code> is a candidate if there is a
          large-ish number of hosts to spread the writes and reads across the keyspace. This
          approach would be useful if scanning by hostname was a priority. </para>
      </section>
      <!--  host lead -->
      <section
        xml:id="schema.casestudies.log-timeseries.revts">
        <title>Timestamp, or Reverse Timestamp?</title>
        <para>If the most important access path is to pull most recent events, then storing the
          timestamps as reverse-timestamps (e.g., <code>timestamp = Long.MAX_VALUE –
            timestamp</code>) will create the property of being able to do a Scan on
            <code>[hostname][log-event]</code> to obtain the quickly obtain the most recently
          captured events. </para>
        <para>Neither approach is wrong, it just depends on what is most appropriate for the
          situation. </para>
        <note>
          <title>Reverse Scan API</title>
          <para>
            <link
              xlink:href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HBASE-4811">HBASE-4811</link>
            implements an API to scan a table or a range within a table in reverse, reducing the
            need to optimize your schema for forward or reverse scanning. This feature is available
            in HBase 0.98 and later. See <link
              xlink:href="https://hbase.apache.org/apidocs/org/apache/hadoop/hbase/client/Scan.html#setReversed%28boolean" />
            for more information. </para>
        </note>
      </section>
      <!--  revts -->
      <section
        xml:id="schema.casestudies.log-timeseries.varkeys">
        <title>Variangle Length or Fixed Length Rowkeys?</title>
        <para>It is critical to remember that rowkeys are stamped on every column in HBase. If the
          hostname is “a” and the event type is “e1” then the resulting rowkey would be quite small.
          However, what if the ingested hostname is “myserver1.mycompany.com” and the event type is
          “com.package1.subpackage2.subsubpackage3.ImportantService”? </para>
        <para>It might make sense to use some substitution in the rowkey. There are at least two
          approaches: hashed and numeric. In the Hostname In The Rowkey Lead Position example, it
          might look like this: </para>
        <para>Composite Rowkey With Hashes:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>[MD5 hash of hostname] = 16 bytes</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>[MD5 hash of event-type] = 16 bytes</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>[timestamp] = 8 bytes</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>Composite Rowkey With Numeric Substitution: </para>
        <para>For this approach another lookup table would be needed in addition to LOG_DATA, called
          LOG_TYPES. The rowkey of LOG_TYPES would be: </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>[type] (e.g., byte indicating hostname vs. event-type)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>[bytes] variable length bytes for raw hostname or event-type.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>A column for this rowkey could be a long with an assigned number, which could be
          obtained by using an <link
            xlink:href="http://hbase.apache.org/apidocs/org/apache/hadoop/hbase/client/HTable.html#incrementColumnValue%28byte[],%20byte[],%20byte[],%20long%29">HBase
            counter</link>. </para>
        <para>So the resulting composite rowkey would be: </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>[substituted long for hostname] = 8 bytes</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>[substituted long for event type] = 8 bytes</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>[timestamp] = 8 bytes</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>In either the Hash or Numeric substitution approach, the raw values for hostname and
          event-type can be stored as columns. </para>
      </section>
      <!--  varkeys -->
    </section>
    <!--  log data and timeseries -->
    <section
      xml:id="schema.casestudies.log-steroids">
      <title>Case Study - Log Data and Timeseries Data on Steroids</title>
      <para>This effectively is the OpenTSDB approach. What OpenTSDB does is re-write data and pack
        rows into columns for certain time-periods. For a detailed explanation, see: <link
          xlink:href="http://opentsdb.net/schema.html">http://opentsdb.net/schema.html</link>, and <link
          xlink:href="http://www.cloudera.com/content/cloudera/en/resources/library/hbasecon/video-hbasecon-2012-lessons-learned-from-opentsdb.html">Lessons
          Learned from OpenTSDB</link> from HBaseCon2012. </para>
      <para>But this is how the general concept works: data is ingested, for example, in this
        manner…</para>
      <screen>
[hostname][log-event][timestamp1]
[hostname][log-event][timestamp2]
[hostname][log-event][timestamp3]
        </screen>
      <para>… with separate rowkeys for each detailed event, but is re-written like this… </para>
      <screen>[hostname][log-event][timerange]</screen>
      <para>… and each of the above events are converted into columns stored with a time-offset
        relative to the beginning timerange (e.g., every 5 minutes). This is obviously a very
        advanced processing technique, but HBase makes this possible. </para>
    </section>
    <!--  log data timeseries steroids -->

    <section
      xml:id="schema.casestudies.custorder">
      <title>Case Study - Customer/Order</title>
      <para>Assume that HBase is used to store customer and order information. There are two core
        record-types being ingested: a Customer record type, and Order record type. </para>
      <para>The Customer record type would include all the things that you’d typically expect: </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Customer number</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Customer name</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Address (e.g., city, state, zip)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Phone numbers, etc.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>The Order record type would include things like: </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Customer number</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Order number</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Sales date</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>A series of nested objects for shipping locations and line-items (see <xref
              linkend="schema.casestudies.custorder.obj" /> for details)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Assuming that the combination of customer number and sales order uniquely identify an
        order, these two attributes will compose the rowkey, and specifically a composite key such
        as: </para>
      <screen>[customer number][order number]</screen>
      <para>… for a ORDER table. However, there are more design decisions to make: are the
          <emphasis>raw</emphasis> values the best choices for rowkeys? </para>
      <para>The same design questions in the Log Data use-case confront us here. What is the
        keyspace of the customer number, and what is the format (e.g., numeric? alphanumeric?) As it
        is advantageous to use fixed-length keys in HBase, as well as keys that can support a
        reasonable spread in the keyspace, similar options appear: </para>
      <para>Composite Rowkey With Hashes: </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>[MD5 of customer number] = 16 bytes</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>[MD5 of order number] = 16 bytes</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Composite Numeric/Hash Combo Rowkey: </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>[substituted long for customer number] = 8 bytes</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>[MD5 of order number] = 16 bytes</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <section
        xml:id="schema.casestudies.custorder.tables">
        <title>Single Table? Multiple Tables?</title>
        <para>A traditional design approach would have separate tables for CUSTOMER and SALES.
          Another option is to pack multiple record types into a single table (e.g., CUSTOMER++). </para>
        <para>Customer Record Type Rowkey: </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>[customer-id]</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>[type] = type indicating ‘1’ for customer record type</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>Order Record Type Rowkey: </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>[customer-id]</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>[type] = type indicating ‘2’ for order record type</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>[order]</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>The advantage of this particular CUSTOMER++ approach is that organizes many different
          record-types by customer-id (e.g., a single scan could get you everything about that
          customer). The disadvantage is that it’s not as easy to scan for a particular record-type.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section
        xml:id="schema.casestudies.custorder.obj">
        <title>Order Object Design</title>
        <para>Now we need to address how to model the Order object. Assume that the class structure
          is as follows:</para>
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Order</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>(an Order can have multiple ShippingLocations</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>LineItem</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>(a ShippingLocation can have multiple LineItems</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        <para>... there are multiple options on storing this data. </para>
        <section
          xml:id="schema.casestudies.custorder.obj.norm">
          <title>Completely Normalized</title>
          <para>With this approach, there would be separate tables for ORDER, SHIPPING_LOCATION, and
            LINE_ITEM. </para>
          <para>The ORDER table's rowkey was described above: <xref
              linkend="schema.casestudies.custorder" />
          </para>
          <para>The SHIPPING_LOCATION's composite rowkey would be something like this: </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>[order-rowkey]</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>[shipping location number] (e.g., 1st location, 2nd, etc.)</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>The LINE_ITEM table's composite rowkey would be something like this: </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>[order-rowkey]</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>[shipping location number] (e.g., 1st location, 2nd, etc.)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>[line item number] (e.g., 1st lineitem, 2nd, etc.)</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>Such a normalized model is likely to be the approach with an RDBMS, but that's not
            your only option with HBase. The cons of such an approach is that to retrieve
            information about any Order, you will need: </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Get on the ORDER table for the Order</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Scan on the SHIPPING_LOCATION table for that order to get the ShippingLocation
                instances</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Scan on the LINE_ITEM for each ShippingLocation</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>... granted, this is what an RDBMS would do under the covers anyway, but since there
            are no joins in HBase you're just more aware of this fact. </para>
        </section>
        <section
          xml:id="schema.casestudies.custorder.obj.rectype">
          <title>Single Table With Record Types</title>
          <para>With this approach, there would exist a single table ORDER that would contain </para>
          <para>The Order rowkey was described above: <xref
              linkend="schema.casestudies.custorder" /></para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>[order-rowkey]</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>[ORDER record type]</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>The ShippingLocation composite rowkey would be something like this: </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>[order-rowkey]</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>[SHIPPING record type]</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>[shipping location number] (e.g., 1st location, 2nd, etc.)</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>The LineItem composite rowkey would be something like this: </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>[order-rowkey]</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>[LINE record type]</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>[shipping location number] (e.g., 1st location, 2nd, etc.)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>[line item number] (e.g., 1st lineitem, 2nd, etc.)</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section
          xml:id="schema.casestudies.custorder.obj.denorm">
          <title>Denormalized</title>
          <para>A variant of the Single Table With Record Types approach is to denormalize and
            flatten some of the object hierarchy, such as collapsing the ShippingLocation attributes
            onto each LineItem instance. </para>
          <para>The LineItem composite rowkey would be something like this: </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>[order-rowkey]</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>[LINE record type]</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>[line item number] (e.g., 1st lineitem, 2nd, etc. - care must be taken that
                there are unique across the entire order)</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>... and the LineItem columns would be something like this: </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>itemNumber</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>quantity</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>price</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>shipToLine1 (denormalized from ShippingLocation)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>shipToLine2 (denormalized from ShippingLocation)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>shipToCity (denormalized from ShippingLocation)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>shipToState (denormalized from ShippingLocation)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>shipToZip (denormalized from ShippingLocation)</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>The pros of this approach include a less complex object heirarchy, but one of the
            cons is that updating gets more complicated in case any of this information changes.
          </para>
        </section>
        <section
          xml:id="schema.casestudies.custorder.obj.singleobj">
          <title>Object BLOB</title>
          <para>With this approach, the entire Order object graph is treated, in one way or another,
            as a BLOB. For example, the ORDER table's rowkey was described above: <xref
              linkend="schema.casestudies.custorder" />, and a single column called "order" would
            contain an object that could be deserialized that contained a container Order,
            ShippingLocations, and LineItems. </para>
          <para>There are many options here: JSON, XML, Java Serialization, Avro, Hadoop Writables,
            etc. All of them are variants of the same approach: encode the object graph to a
            byte-array. Care should be taken with this approach to ensure backward compatibilty in
            case the object model changes such that older persisted structures can still be read
            back out of HBase. </para>
          <para>Pros are being able to manage complex object graphs with minimal I/O (e.g., a single
            HBase Get per Order in this example), but the cons include the aforementioned warning
            about backward compatiblity of serialization, language dependencies of serialization
            (e.g., Java Serialization only works with Java clients), the fact that you have to
            deserialize the entire object to get any piece of information inside the BLOB, and the
            difficulty in getting frameworks like Hive to work with custom objects like this.
          </para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <!--  cust/order order object -->
    </section>
    <!--  cust/order -->

    <section
      xml:id="schema.smackdown">
      <title>Case Study - "Tall/Wide/Middle" Schema Design Smackdown</title>
      <para>This section will describe additional schema design questions that appear on the
        dist-list, specifically about tall and wide tables. These are general guidelines and not
        laws - each application must consider its own needs. </para>
      <section
        xml:id="schema.smackdown.rowsversions">
        <title>Rows vs. Versions</title>
        <para>A common question is whether one should prefer rows or HBase's built-in-versioning.
          The context is typically where there are "a lot" of versions of a row to be retained
          (e.g., where it is significantly above the HBase default of 1 max versions). The
          rows-approach would require storing a timestamp in some portion of the rowkey so that they
          would not overwite with each successive update. </para>
        <para>Preference: Rows (generally speaking). </para>
      </section>
      <section
        xml:id="schema.smackdown.rowscols">
        <title>Rows vs. Columns</title>
        <para>Another common question is whether one should prefer rows or columns. The context is
          typically in extreme cases of wide tables, such as having 1 row with 1 million attributes,
          or 1 million rows with 1 columns apiece. </para>
        <para>Preference: Rows (generally speaking). To be clear, this guideline is in the context
          is in extremely wide cases, not in the standard use-case where one needs to store a few
          dozen or hundred columns. But there is also a middle path between these two options, and
          that is "Rows as Columns." </para>
      </section>
      <section
        xml:id="schema.smackdown.rowsascols">
        <title>Rows as Columns</title>
        <para>The middle path between Rows vs. Columns is packing data that would be a separate row
          into columns, for certain rows. OpenTSDB is the best example of this case where a single
          row represents a defined time-range, and then discrete events are treated as columns. This
          approach is often more complex, and may require the additional complexity of re-writing
          your data, but has the advantage of being I/O efficient. For an overview of this approach,
          see <xref
            linkend="schema.casestudies.log-steroids" />. </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <!--  note:  the following id is not consistent with the others becaus it was formerly in the Case Studies chapter,
	    but I didn't want to break backward compatibility of the link.  But future entries should look like the above case-study
	    links (schema.casestudies. ...)  -->
    <section
      xml:id="casestudies.schema.listdata">
      <title>Case Study - List Data</title>
      <para>The following is an exchange from the user dist-list regarding a fairly common question:
        how to handle per-user list data in Apache HBase. </para>
      <para>*** QUESTION ***</para>
      <para> We're looking at how to store a large amount of (per-user) list data in HBase, and we
        were trying to figure out what kind of access pattern made the most sense. One option is
        store the majority of the data in a key, so we could have something like: </para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[
<FixedWidthUserName><FixedWidthValueId1>:"" (no value)
<FixedWidthUserName><FixedWidthValueId2>:"" (no value)
<FixedWidthUserName><FixedWidthValueId3>:"" (no value)
]]></programlisting>

      <para>The other option we had was to do this entirely using:</para>
      <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<FixedWidthUserName><FixedWidthPageNum0>:<FixedWidthLength><FixedIdNextPageNum><ValueId1><ValueId2><ValueId3>...
<FixedWidthUserName><FixedWidthPageNum1>:<FixedWidthLength><FixedIdNextPageNum><ValueId1><ValueId2><ValueId3>...
    		]]></programlisting>
      <para> where each row would contain multiple values. So in one case reading the first thirty
        values would be: </para>
      <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
scan { STARTROW => 'FixedWidthUsername' LIMIT => 30}
    		]]></programlisting>
      <para>And in the second case it would be </para>
      <programlisting>
get 'FixedWidthUserName\x00\x00\x00\x00'
    		</programlisting>
      <para> The general usage pattern would be to read only the first 30 values of these lists,
        with infrequent access reading deeper into the lists. Some users would have &lt;= 30 total
        values in these lists, and some users would have millions (i.e. power-law distribution) </para>
      <para> The single-value format seems like it would take up more space on HBase, but would
        offer some improved retrieval / pagination flexibility. Would there be any significant
        performance advantages to be able to paginate via gets vs paginating with scans? </para>
      <para> My initial understanding was that doing a scan should be faster if our paging size is
        unknown (and caching is set appropriately), but that gets should be faster if we'll always
        need the same page size. I've ended up hearing different people tell me opposite things
        about performance. I assume the page sizes would be relatively consistent, so for most use
        cases we could guarantee that we only wanted one page of data in the fixed-page-length case.
        I would also assume that we would have infrequent updates, but may have inserts into the
        middle of these lists (meaning we'd need to update all subsequent rows). </para>
      <para> Thanks for help / suggestions / follow-up questions. </para>
      <para>*** ANSWER ***</para>
      <para> If I understand you correctly, you're ultimately trying to store triples in the form
        "user, valueid, value", right? E.g., something like: </para>
      <programlisting>
"user123, firstname, Paul",
"user234, lastname, Smith"
			</programlisting>
      <para> (But the usernames are fixed width, and the valueids are fixed width). </para>
      <para> And, your access pattern is along the lines of: "for user X, list the next 30 values,
        starting with valueid Y". Is that right? And these values should be returned sorted by
        valueid? </para>
      <para> The tl;dr version is that you should probably go with one row per user+value, and not
        build a complicated intra-row pagination scheme on your own unless you're really sure it is
        needed. </para>
      <para> Your two options mirror a common question people have when designing HBase schemas:
        should I go "tall" or "wide"? Your first schema is "tall": each row represents one value for
        one user, and so there are many rows in the table for each user; the row key is user +
        valueid, and there would be (presumably) a single column qualifier that means "the value".
        This is great if you want to scan over rows in sorted order by row key (thus my question
        above, about whether these ids are sorted correctly). You can start a scan at any
        user+valueid, read the next 30, and be done. What you're giving up is the ability to have
        transactional guarantees around all the rows for one user, but it doesn't sound like you
        need that. Doing it this way is generally recommended (see here <link
          xlink:href="http://hbase.apache.org/book.html#schema.smackdown">http://hbase.apache.org/book.html#schema.smackdown</link>). </para>
      <para> Your second option is "wide": you store a bunch of values in one row, using different
        qualifiers (where the qualifier is the valueid). The simple way to do that would be to just
        store ALL values for one user in a single row. I'm guessing you jumped to the "paginated"
        version because you're assuming that storing millions of columns in a single row would be
        bad for performance, which may or may not be true; as long as you're not trying to do too
        much in a single request, or do things like scanning over and returning all of the cells in
        the row, it shouldn't be fundamentally worse. The client has methods that allow you to get
        specific slices of columns. </para>
      <para> Note that neither case fundamentally uses more disk space than the other; you're just
        "shifting" part of the identifying information for a value either to the left (into the row
        key, in option one) or to the right (into the column qualifiers in option 2). Under the
        covers, every key/value still stores the whole row key, and column family name. (If this is
        a bit confusing, take an hour and watch Lars George's excellent video about understanding
        HBase schema design: <link
          xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_HLoH_PgrLk)">http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_HLoH_PgrLk)</link>. </para>
      <para> A manually paginated version has lots more complexities, as you note, like having to
        keep track of how many things are in each page, re-shuffling if new values are inserted,
        etc. That seems significantly more complex. It might have some slight speed advantages (or
        disadvantages!) at extremely high throughput, and the only way to really know that would be
        to try it out. If you don't have time to build it both ways and compare, my advice would be
        to start with the simplest option (one row per user+value). Start simple and iterate! :)
      </para>
    </section>
    <!--  listdata -->

  </section>
  <!--  schema design cases -->
  <section
    xml:id="schema.ops">
    <title>Operational and Performance Configuration Options</title>
    <para>See the Performance section <xref
        linkend="perf.schema" /> for more information operational and performance schema design
      options, such as Bloom Filters, Table-configured regionsizes, compression, and blocksizes.
    </para>
  </section>

</chapter>
<!--  schema design -->
