<?xml version="1.0"?>
<chapter
    xml:id="upgrading"
    version="5.0"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <!--
/**
 * Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 * or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 * distributed with this work for additional information
 * regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 * to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 * "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 * with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 *
 *     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 *
 * Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 * distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 * WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 * See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 * limitations under the License.
 */
-->
    <title>Upgrading</title>


    <para>You cannot skip major versions upgrading. If you are upgrading from version 0.90.x to
        0.94.x, you must first go from 0.90.x to 0.92.x and then go from 0.92.x to 0.94.x.</para>
    <note>
        <para>It may be possible to skip across versions -- for example go from 0.92.2 straight to
            0.98.0 just following the 0.96.x upgrade instructions -- but we have not tried it so
            cannot say whether it works or not.</para>
    </note>
    <para> Review <xref
            linkend="configuration" />, in particular the section on Hadoop version. </para>
    <section
        xml:id="hbase.versioning">
        <title>HBase version number and compatibility</title>
        <para>HBase has two versioning schemes, pre-1.0 and post-1.0. Both are detailed below. </para>
		    
	    <section xml:id="hbase.versioning.post10">
		  <title>Post 1.0 versions</title>
		  <para>Starting with 1.0.0 release, HBase uses <link xlink:href="http://semver.org/">Semantic Versioning</link> for it release versioning.
		In summary:
		<blockquote>
	    <para>
		Given a version number MAJOR.MINOR.PATCH, increment the:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>MAJOR version when you make incompatible API changes,</listitem>
          <listitem>MINOR version when you add functionality in a backwards-compatible manner, and</listitem>
          <listitem>PATCH version when you make backwards-compatible bug fixes.</listitem>
          <listitem>Additional labels for pre-release and build metadata are available as extensions to the MAJOR.MINOR.PATCH format.</listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        </blockquote>
		</para>

	    <section xml:id="hbase.versioning.compat">
		  <title>Compatibility Dimensions</title>	
		<para>In addition to the usual API versioning considerations HBase has other compatibility dimensions that we need to consider.</para>

	    <section>
		  <title>Client-Server wire protocol compatibility</title>	
            <para><itemizedlist>
              <listitem>Allows updating client and server out of sync.</listitem>
              <listitem>We could only allow upgrading the server first. I.e. the server would be backward compatible to an old client, that way new APIs are OK.</listitem>
              <listitem>Example: A user should be able to use an old client to connect to an upgraded cluster.</listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        </section>
	    <section>
		  <title>Server-Server protocol compatibility</title>	
          <para><itemizedlist>
	        <listitem>Servers of different versions can co-exist in the same cluster.</listitem>
	        <listitem>The wire protocol between servers is compatible.</listitem>
	        <listitem>Workers for distributed tasks, such as replication and log splitting, can co-exist in the same cluster.</listitem>
	        <listitem>Dependent protocols (such as using ZK for coordination) will also not be changed.</listitem>
	        <listitem>Example: A user can perform a rolling upgrade.</listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para> 
        </section>
	    <section>
		  <title>File format compatibility</title>
          <para><itemizedlist>
	        <listitem>Support file formats backward and forward compatible</listitem>
	        <listitem>Example: File, ZK encoding, directory layout is upgraded automatically as part of an HBase upgrade. User can rollback to the older version and everything will continue to work.</listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para> 
        </section>
	    <section>
		  <title>Client API compatibility</title>	
          <para><itemizedlist>
	        <listitem>Allow changing or removing existing client APIs.</listitem>
	        <listitem>An API needs to deprecated for a major version before we will change/remove it.</listitem>
	        <listitem>Example: A user using a newly deprecated api does not need to modify application code with hbase api calls until the next major version.</listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para> 
        </section>
	    <section>
		  <title>Client Binary compatibility</title>	
          <para><itemizedlist>
	        <listitem>Old client code can run unchanged (no recompilation needed) against new jars.</listitem>
	        <listitem>Example: Old compiled client code will work unchanged with the new jars.</listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para> 
        </section>
	    <section>
		  <title>Server-Side Limited API compatibility (taken from Hadoop)</title>	
          <para><itemizedlist>
	        <listitem>Internal APIs are marked as Stable, Evolving, or Unstable</listitem>
	        <listitem>This implies binary compatibility for coprocessors and plugins (pluggable classes, including replication) as long as these are only using marked interfaces/classes.</listitem>
	        <listitem>Example: Old compiled Coprocessor, Filter, or Plugin code will work unchanged with the new jars.</listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para> 
        </section>
	    <section>
		  <title>Dependency Compatibility</title>	
          <para><itemizedlist>
	        <listitem>An upgrade of HBase will not require an incompatible upgrade of a dependent project, including the Java runtime.</listitem>
	        <listitem>Example: An upgrade of Hadoop will not invalidate any of the compatibilities guarantees we made.</listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para> 
        </section>
	    <section>
		  <title>Operational Compatibility</title>	
          <para><itemizedlist>
	        <listitem>Metric changes</listitem>
	        <listitem>Behavioral changes of services</listitem>
	        <listitem>Web page APIs</listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para> 
        </section>
	    <section>
		  <title>Summary</title>	
            <para><itemizedlist>
	          <listitem>A patch upgrade is a drop-in replacement. Any change that is not Java binary compatible would not be allowed.<footnote><link xlink:href="http://docs.oracle.com/javase/specs/jls/se7/html/jls-13.html"/></footnote></listitem>
	          <listitem>A minor upgrade requires no application/client code modification. Ideally it would be a drop-in replacement but client code, coprocessors, filters, etc might have to be recompiled if new jars are used.</listitem>
	          <listitem>A major upgrade allows the HBase community to make breaking changes.</listitem> 
          </itemizedlist></para> 
        </section>
   	    <section>
		  <title>Compatibility Matrix <footnote><para>Note that this indicates what could break, not that it will break. We will/should add specifics in our release notes.</para></footnote></title>	
           <para> (Y means we support the compatibility. N means we can break it.) </para>
      <table>
        <title>Compatibility Matrix</title>
        <tgroup
          cols="4"
          align="left"
          colsep="1"
          rowsep="1">
          <colspec
            colname="c1"
            align="left" />
          <colspec
            colname="c2"
            align="center" />
          <colspec
            colname="c3"
            align="center" />
          <colspec
            colname="c4"
            align="center" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry> </entry>
              <entry>Major</entry>
              <entry>Minor</entry>
              <entry>Patch</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Client-Server wire Compatibility</entry>
              <entry>N</entry>
              <entry>Y</entry>
              <entry>Y</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Server-Server Compatibility</entry>
              <entry>N</entry>
              <entry>Y</entry>
              <entry>Y</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>File Format Compatibility</entry>
              <entry>N<footnote><para>Running an offline upgrade tool without rollback might be needed. We will typically only support migrating data from major version X to major version X+1.
</para></footnote></entry>
              <entry>Y</entry>
              <entry>Y</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Client API Compatibility</entry>
              <entry>N</entry>
              <entry>Y</entry>
              <entry>Y</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Client Binary Compatibility</entry>
              <entry>N</entry>
              <entry>N</entry>
              <entry>Y</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Server-Side Limited API Compatibility</entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><itemizedlist><listitem>Stable</listitem></itemizedlist></entry>
              <entry>N</entry>
              <entry>Y</entry>
              <entry>Y</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><itemizedlist><listitem>Evolving</listitem></itemizedlist></entry>
              <entry>N</entry>
              <entry>N</entry>
              <entry>Y</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><itemizedlist><listitem>Unstable</listitem></itemizedlist></entry>
              <entry>N</entry>
              <entry>N</entry>
              <entry>N</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Dependency Compatibility</entry>
              <entry>N</entry>
              <entry>Y</entry>
              <entry>Y</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Operational Compatibility</entry>
              <entry>N</entry>
              <entry>N</entry>
              <entry>Y</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </section>

	    <section xml:id="hbase.client.api">
		  <title>HBase API surface</title>
		  <para> HBase has a lot of API points, but for the compatibility matrix above, we differentiate between Client API, Limited Private API, and Private API. HBase uses a version of 
		  <link xlink:href="https://hadoop.apache.org/docs/current/hadoop-project-dist/hadoop-common/Compatibility.html">Hadoop's Interface classification</link>. HBase's Interface classification classes can be found <link xlink:href="https://hbase.apache.org/apidocs/org/apache/hadoop/hbase/classification/package-summary.html"> here</link>. 
		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>InterfaceAudience: captures the intended audience, possible values are Public (for end users and external projects), LimitedPrivate (for other Projects, Coprocessors or other plugin points), and Private (for internal use).</listitem>
        <listitem>InterfaceStability: describes what types of interface changes are permitted. Possible values are Stable, Evolving, Unstable, and Deprecated.</listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
		</para>
		
       <section xml:id="hbase.client.api">
		  <title>HBase Client API</title>
		  <para>HBase Client API consists of all the classes or methods that are marked with InterfaceAudience.Public interface. All main classes in hbase-client and dependent modules have either InterfaceAudience.Public, InterfaceAudience.LimitedPrivate, or InterfaceAudience.Private marker. Not all classes in other modules (hbase-server, etc) have the marker. If a class is not annotated with one of these, it is assumed to be a InterfaceAudience.Private class. </para>
        </section>

       <section xml:id="hbase.limitetprivate.api">
		  <title>HBase LimitedPrivate API</title>
		  <para>LimitedPrivate annotation comes with a set of target consumers for the interfaces. Those consumers are coprocessors, phoenix, replication endpoint implemnetations or similar.   At this point, HBase only guarantees source and binary compatibility for these interfaces between patch versions. </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="hbase.private.api">
		  <title>HBase Private API</title>
		  <para>All classes annotated with InterfaceAudience.Private or all classes that do not have the annotation are for HBase internal use only. The interfaces and method signatures can change at any point in time. If you are relying on a particular interface that is marked Private, you should open a jira to propose changing the interface to be Public or LimitedPrivate, or an interface exposed for this purpose. </para>
        </section>

        </section>
        </section>
		
	    </section>
	
	    <section xml:id="hbase.versioning.pre10">
		  <title>Pre 1.0 versions</title>
		  <para></para>

        <para> Before the semantic versioning scheme pre-1.0, HBase tracked either Hadoop's versions (0.2x) 
	           or 0.9x versions. If you are into the arcane, checkout our old wiki page on <link
                xlink:href="http://wiki.apache.org/hadoop/Hbase/HBaseVersions">HBase
                Versioning</link> which tries to connect the HBase version dots. Below sections cover ONLY the 
                releases before 1.0.</para>
        <section
            xml:id="hbase.development.series">
            <title>Odd/Even Versioning or "Development"" Series Releases</title>
            <para>Ahead of big releases, we have been putting up preview versions to start the
                feedback cycle turning-over earlier. These "Development" Series releases, always
                odd-numbered, come with no guarantees, not even regards being able to upgrade
                between two sequential releases (we reserve the right to break compatibility across
                "Development" Series releases). Needless to say, these releases are not for
                production deploys. They are a preview of what is coming in the hope that interested
                parties will take the release for a test drive and flag us early if we there are
                issues we've missed ahead of our rolling a production-worthy release. </para>
            <para>Our first "Development" Series was the 0.89 set that came out ahead of HBase
                0.90.0. HBase 0.95 is another "Development" Series that portends HBase 0.96.0.
                0.99.x is the last series in "developer preview" mode before 1.0. Afterwards, 
                we will be using semantic versioning naming scheme (see above).
            </para>
        </section>
        <section
            xml:id="hbase.binary.compatibility">
            <title>Binary Compatibility</title>
            <para>When we say two HBase versions are compatible, we mean that the versions are wire
                and binary compatible. Compatible HBase versions means that clients can talk to
                compatible but differently versioned servers. It means too that you can just swap
                out the jars of one version and replace them with the jars of another, compatible
                version and all will just work. Unless otherwise specified, HBase point versions are
                (mostly) binary compatible. You can safely do rolling upgrades between binary compatible
                versions; i.e. across point versions: e.g. from 0.94.5 to 0.94.6. See <link
                xlink:href="http://search-hadoop.com/m/bOOvwHGW981/Does+compatibility+between+versions+also+mean+binary+compatibility%253F&amp;subj=Re+">Does
                            compatibility between versions also mean binary compatibility?</link>
                        discussion on the hbaes dev mailing list. </para>
        </section>

 
	    </section>
        <section xml:id="hbase.rolling.upgrade">
          <title><firstterm>Rolling Upgrades</firstterm></title>
          <para>A rolling upgrade is the process by which you update the servers
            in your cluster a server at a time. You can rolling upgrade across HBase versions
            if they are binary or wire compatible.
            See <xlnk href="hbase.rolling.restart" /> for more on what this means.
            Coarsely, a rolling upgrade is a graceful stop each server,
            update the software, and then restart.  You do this for each server in the cluster.
            Usually you upgrade the Master first and then the regionservers.
            See <xlink href="rolling" /> for tools that can help use the rolling upgrade process.
          </para>
          <para>For example, in the below, hbase was symlinked to the actual hbase install.
            On upgrade, before running a rolling restart over the cluser, we changed the symlink
            to point at the new HBase software version and then ran 
            <programlisting>$ HADOOP_HOME=~/hadoop-2.6.0-CRC-SNAPSHOT ~/hbase/bin/rolling-restart.sh --config ~/conf_hbase</programlisting>
            The rolling-restart script will first gracefully stop and restart the master, and then
            each of the regionservers in turn. Because the symlink was changed, on restart the
            server will come up using the new hbase version.  Check logs for errors as the
            rolling upgrade proceeds.
          </para>
        <section
            xml:id="hbase.rolling.restart">
            <title>Rolling Upgrade between versions that are Binary/Wire compatibile</title>
            <para>Unless otherwise specified, HBase point versions are binary compatible. You can do
              a <xlink href="hbase.rolling.upgrade" /> between hbase point versions.
                For example, you can go to 0.94.6 from 0.94.5 by doing a rolling upgrade
                across the cluster replacing the 0.94.5 binary with a 0.94.6 binary.</para>
              <para>In the minor version-particular sections below, we call out where the versions
                are wire/protocol compatible and in this case, it is also possible to do a
                <xlink href="hbase.rolling.upgrade" />. For example, in
            <xlink href="upgrade1.0.rolling.upgrade" />, we
              state that it is possible to do a rolling upgrade between hbase-0.98.x and hbase-1.0.0.</para>
        </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="upgrade1.0">
        <title>Upgrading from 0.98.x to 1.0.x</title>
        <para>In this section we first note the significant changes that come in with 1.0.0 HBase and then
          we go over the upgrade process.  Be sure to read the significant changes section with care
          so you avoid surprises.
        </para>
        <section xml:id="upgrade1.0.changes">
            <title>Changes of Note!</title>
            <para>In here we list important changes that are in 1.0.0 since 0.98.x., changes you should
            be aware that will go into effect once you upgrade.</para>
            <section xml:id="zookeeper.3.4"><title>ZooKeeper 3.4 is required in HBase 1.0.0</title>
              <para>See <xref linkend="zookeeper.requirements" />.</para>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="default.ports.changed"><title>HBase Default Ports Changed</title>
              <para>The ports used by HBase changed.  The used to be in the 600XX range.  In
                hbase-1.0.0 they have been moved up out of the ephemeral port range and are
                160XX instead (Master web UI was 60010 and is now 16030; the RegionServer
                web UI was 60030 and is now 16030, etc). If you want to keep the old port
                locations, copy the port setting configs from <filename>hbase-default.xml</filename>
                into <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>, change them back to the old values
                from hbase-0.98.x era, and ensure you've distributed your configurations before
              you restart.</para>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="upgrade1.0.hbase.bucketcache.percentage.in.combinedcache">
                <title>hbase.bucketcache.percentage.in.combinedcache configuration has been REMOVED</title>
                <para>You may have made use of this configuration if you are using BucketCache.
                    If NOT using BucketCache, this change does not effect you.
                    Its removal means that your L1 LruBlockCache is now sized
                    using <varname>hfile.block.cache.size</varname> -- i.e. the way you
                    would size the onheap L1 LruBlockCache if you were NOT doing
                    BucketCache -- and the BucketCache size is not whatever the
                    setting for hbase.bucketcache.size is.  You may need to adjust
                    configs to get the LruBlockCache and BucketCache sizes set to
                    what they were in 0.98.x and previous.  If you did not set this
                    config., its default value was 0.9.  If you do nothing, your
                    BucketCache will increase in size by 10%.  Your L1 LruBlockCache will
                    become <varname>hfile.block.cache.size</varname> times your java
                    heap size (hfile.block.cache.size is a float between 0.0 and 1.0).
                    To read more, see
                    <link xlink:href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HBASE-11520">HBASE-11520 Simplify offheap cache config by removing the confusing "hbase.bucketcache.percentage.in.combinedcache"</link>.
                </para>
          </section>
          <section xml:id="hbase-12068"><title>If you have your own customer filters....</title>
            <para>See the release notes on the issue <link xlink:href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HBASE-12068">HBASE-12068 [Branch-1] Avoid need to always do KeyValueUtil#ensureKeyValue for Filter transformCell</link>;
              be sure to follow the recommendations therein.
            </para>
          </section>
          <section xml:id="dlr"><title>Distributed Log Replay</title>
            <para>
              <xref linkend="distributed.log.replay" /> is off by default in hbase-1.0.
                Enabling it can make a big difference improving HBase MTTR. Enable this
                feature if you are doing a clean stop/start when you are upgrading.
                You cannot rolling upgrade on to this feature (caveat if you are running
                on a version of hbase in excess of hbase-0.98.4 -- see
                <link xlink:href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HBASE-12577">HBASE-12577 Disable distributed log replay by default</link> for more).
            </para>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="upgrade1.0.rolling.upgrade">
          <title>Rolling upgrade from 0.98.x to HBase 1.0.0</title>
          <note><title>From 0.96.x to 1.0.0</title>
            <para>You cannot do a <xlink href="rolling.upgrade" /> from 0.96.x to 1.0.0 without
              first doing a rolling upgrade to 0.98.x. See comment in
              <link xlink:href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HBASE-11164?focusedCommentId=14182330&amp;page=com.atlassian.jira.plugin.system.issuetabpanels:comment-tabpanel&#35;comment-14182330">HBASE-11164 Document and test rolling updates from 0.98 -> 1.0</link> for the why.
              Also because hbase-1.0.0 enables hfilev3 by default,
              <link xlink:href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HBASE-9801">HBASE-9801 Change the default HFile version to V3</link>,
              and support for hfilev3 only arrives in 0.98, this is another reason you cannot rolling upgrade from hbase-0.96.x;
              if the rolling upgrade stalls, the 0.96.x servers cannot open files written by the servers running the newer hbase-1.0.0
              hfilev3 writing servers.
            </para>
          </note>
          <para>There are no known issues running a <xlink href="hbase.rolling.upgrade" /> from hbase-0.98.x to hbase-1.0.0.
          
          </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="upgrade1.0.from.0.94">
          <title>Upgrading to 1.0 from 0.94</title>
          <para>You cannot rolling upgrade from 0.94.x to 1.x.x.  You must stop your cluster,
            install the 1.x.x software, run the migration described at <xref linkend="executing.the.0.96.upgrade" />
            (substituting 1.x.x. wherever we make mention of 0.96.x in the section below),
            and then restart.  Be sure to upgrade your zookeeper if it is a version less than the required 3.4.x.
          </para>

        </section>
    </section>

    <section
        xml:id="upgrade0.98">
        <title>Upgrading from 0.96.x to 0.98.x</title>
        <para>A rolling upgrade from 0.96.x to 0.98.x works. The two versions are not binary
            compatible.</para>
        <para>Additional steps are required to take advantage of some of the new features of 0.98.x,
            including cell visibility labels, cell ACLs, and transparent server side encryption. See
            the <xref
                linkend="security" /> chapter of this guide for more information. Significant
            performance improvements include a change to the write ahead log threading model that
            provides higher transaction throughput under high load, reverse scanners, MapReduce over
            snapshot files, and striped compaction.</para>
        <para>Clients and servers can run with 0.98.x and 0.96.x versions. However, applications may
            need to be recompiled due to changes in the Java API.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Upgrading from 0.94.x to 0.98.x</title>
        <para> A rolling upgrade from 0.94.x directly to 0.98.x does not work. The upgrade path
            follows the same procedures as <xref
                linkend="upgrade0.96" />. Additional steps are required to use some of the new
            features of 0.98.x. See <xref
                linkend="upgrade0.98" /> for an abbreviated list of these features. </para>
    </section>
    <section
        xml:id="upgrade0.96">
        <title>Upgrading from 0.94.x to 0.96.x</title>
        <subtitle>The "Singularity"</subtitle>
        <note><title>HBase 0.96.x was EOL'd, September 1st, 2014</title><para>
            Do not deploy 0.96.x  Deploy a 0.98.x at least.
            See <link xlink:href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HBASE-11642">EOL 0.96</link>.
        </para></note>

        <para>You will have to stop your old 0.94.x cluster completely to upgrade. If you are
            replicating between clusters, both clusters will have to go down to upgrade. Make sure
            it is a clean shutdown. The less WAL files around, the faster the upgrade will run (the
            upgrade will split any log files it finds in the filesystem as part of the upgrade
            process). All clients must be upgraded to 0.96 too. </para>
        <para>The API has changed. You will need to recompile your code against 0.96 and you may
            need to adjust applications to go against new APIs (TODO: List of changes). </para>
        <section xml:id="executing.the.0.96.upgrade">
            <title>Executing the 0.96 Upgrade</title>
            <note>
              <title>HDFS and ZooKeeper must be up!</title>
                <para>HDFS and ZooKeeper should be up and running during the upgrade process.</para>
            </note>
            <para>hbase-0.96.0 comes with an upgrade script. Run
                <programlisting language="bourne">$ bin/hbase upgrade</programlisting> to see its usage. The script
                has two main modes: -check, and -execute. </para>
            <section>
                <title>check</title>
                <para>The <emphasis>check</emphasis> step is run against a running 0.94 cluster. Run
                    it from a downloaded 0.96.x binary. The <emphasis>check</emphasis> step is
                    looking for the presence of <filename>HFileV1</filename> files. These are
                    unsupported in hbase-0.96.0. To purge them -- have them rewritten as HFileV2 --
                    you must run a compaction. </para>
                <para>The <emphasis>check</emphasis> step prints stats at the end of its run (grep
                    for “Result:” in the log) printing absolute path of the tables it scanned, any
                    HFileV1 files found, the regions containing said files (the regions we need to
                    major compact to purge the HFileV1s), and any corrupted files if any found. A
                    corrupt file is unreadable, and so is undefined (neither HFileV1 nor HFileV2). </para>
                <para>To run the check step, run <command>$ bin/hbase upgrade -check</command>. Here
                    is sample output:</para>
                <screen>
Tables Processed:
hdfs://localhost:41020/myHBase/.META.
hdfs://localhost:41020/myHBase/usertable
hdfs://localhost:41020/myHBase/TestTable
hdfs://localhost:41020/myHBase/t

Count of HFileV1: 2
HFileV1:
hdfs://localhost:41020/myHBase/usertable    /fa02dac1f38d03577bd0f7e666f12812/family/249450144068442524
hdfs://localhost:41020/myHBase/usertable    /ecdd3eaee2d2fcf8184ac025555bb2af/family/249450144068442512

Count of corrupted files: 1
Corrupted Files:
hdfs://localhost:41020/myHBase/usertable/fa02dac1f38d03577bd0f7e666f12812/family/1
Count of Regions with HFileV1: 2
Regions to Major Compact:
hdfs://localhost:41020/myHBase/usertable/fa02dac1f38d03577bd0f7e666f12812
hdfs://localhost:41020/myHBase/usertable/ecdd3eaee2d2fcf8184ac025555bb2af

There are some HFileV1, or corrupt files (files with incorrect major version)
                </screen>
                <para>In the above sample output, there are two HFileV1 in two regions, and one
                    corrupt file. Corrupt files should probably be removed. The regions that have
                    HFileV1s need to be major compacted. To major compact, start up the hbase shell
                    and review how to compact an individual region. After the major compaction is
                    done, rerun the check step and the HFileV1s shoudl be gone, replaced by HFileV2
                    instances. </para>
                <para>By default, the check step scans the hbase root directory (defined as
                    hbase.rootdir in the configuration). To scan a specific directory only, pass the
                        <emphasis>-dir</emphasis> option.</para>
                <screen language="bourne">$ bin/hbase upgrade -check -dir /myHBase/testTable</screen>
                <para>The above command would detect HFileV1s in the /myHBase/testTable directory. </para>
                <para> Once the check step reports all the HFileV1 files have been rewritten, it is
                    safe to proceed with the upgrade. </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>execute</title>
                <para>After the check step shows the cluster is free of HFileV1, it is safe to
                    proceed with the upgrade. Next is the <emphasis>execute</emphasis> step. You
                    must <emphasis>SHUTDOWN YOUR 0.94.x CLUSTER</emphasis> before you can run the
                        <emphasis>execute</emphasis> step. The execute step will not run if it
                    detects running HBase masters or regionservers. <note>
                        <para>HDFS and ZooKeeper should be up and running during the upgrade
                            process. If zookeeper is managed by HBase, then you can start zookeeper
                            so it is available to the upgrade by running <command>$
                                ./hbase/bin/hbase-daemon.sh start zookeeper</command>
                        </para>
                    </note>
                </para>
                <para> The <emphasis>execute</emphasis> upgrade step is made of three substeps. </para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Namespaces: HBase 0.96.0 has support for namespaces. The upgrade needs
                            to reorder directories in the filesystem for namespaces to work.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>ZNodes: All znodes are purged so that new ones can be written in their
                            place using a new protobuf'ed format and a few are migrated in place:
                            e.g. replication and table state znodes</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>WAL Log Splitting: If the 0.94.x cluster shutdown was not clean, we'll
                            split WAL logs as part of migration before we startup on 0.96.0. This
                            WAL splitting runs slower than the native distributed WAL splitting
                            because it is all inside the single upgrade process (so try and get a
                            clean shutdown of the 0.94.0 cluster if you can). </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para> To run the <emphasis>execute</emphasis> step, make sure that first you have
                    copied hbase-0.96.0 binaries everywhere under servers and under clients. Make
                    sure the 0.94.0 cluster is down. Then do as follows:</para>
                <screen language="bourne">$ bin/hbase upgrade -execute</screen>
                <para>Here is some sample output.</para>
                <programlisting>
Starting Namespace upgrade
Created version file at hdfs://localhost:41020/myHBase with version=7
Migrating table testTable to hdfs://localhost:41020/myHBase/.data/default/testTable
…..
Created version file at hdfs://localhost:41020/myHBase with version=8
Successfully completed NameSpace upgrade.
Starting Znode upgrade
….
Successfully completed Znode upgrade

Starting Log splitting
…
Successfully completed Log splitting
         </programlisting>
                <para> If the output from the execute step looks good, stop the zookeeper instance
                    you started to do the upgrade:
                    <programlisting language="bourne">$ ./hbase/bin/hbase-daemon.sh stop zookeeper</programlisting>
                    Now start up hbase-0.96.0. </para>
            </section>
            <section
                xml:id="s096.migration.troubleshooting">
                <title>Troubleshooting</title>
                <section
                    xml:id="s096.migration.troubleshooting.old.client">
                    <title>Old Client connecting to 0.96 cluster</title>
                    <para>It will fail with an exception like the below. Upgrade.</para>
                    <screen>17:22:15  Exception in thread "main" java.lang.IllegalArgumentException: Not a host:port pair: PBUF
17:22:15  *
17:22:15   api-compat-8.ent.cloudera.com ��  ���(
17:22:15    at org.apache.hadoop.hbase.util.Addressing.parseHostname(Addressing.java:60)
17:22:15    at org.apache.hadoop.hbase.ServerName.&amp;init>(ServerName.java:101)
17:22:15    at org.apache.hadoop.hbase.ServerName.parseVersionedServerName(ServerName.java:283)
17:22:15    at org.apache.hadoop.hbase.MasterAddressTracker.bytesToServerName(MasterAddressTracker.java:77)
17:22:15    at org.apache.hadoop.hbase.MasterAddressTracker.getMasterAddress(MasterAddressTracker.java:61)
17:22:15    at org.apache.hadoop.hbase.client.HConnectionManager$HConnectionImplementation.getMaster(HConnectionManager.java:703)
17:22:15    at org.apache.hadoop.hbase.client.HBaseAdmin.&amp;init>(HBaseAdmin.java:126)
17:22:15    at Client_4_3_0.setup(Client_4_3_0.java:716)
17:22:15    at Client_4_3_0.main(Client_4_3_0.java:63)</screen>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Upgrading <code>META</code> to use Protocol Buffers (Protobuf)</title>
                <para>When you upgrade from versions prior to 0.96, <code>META</code> needs to be
                    converted to use protocol buffers. This is controlled by the configuration
                    option <option>hbase.MetaMigrationConvertingToPB</option>, which is set to
                        <literal>true</literal> by default. Therefore, by default, no action is
                    required on your part.</para>
                <para>The migration is a one-time event. However, every time your cluster starts,
                        <code>META</code> is scanned to ensure that it does not need to be
                    converted. If you have a very large number of regions, this scan can take a long
                    time. Starting in 0.98.5, you can set
                        <option>hbase.MetaMigrationConvertingToPB</option> to
                        <literal>false</literal> in <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>, to disable
                    this start-up scan. This should be considered an expert-level setting.</para>
            </section>
        </section>


    </section>

    <section
        xml:id="upgrade0.94">
        <title>Upgrading from 0.92.x to 0.94.x</title>
        <para>We used to think that 0.92 and 0.94 were interface compatible and that you can do a
            rolling upgrade between these versions but then we figured that <link
                xlink:href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HBASE-5357">HBASE-5357 Use builder
                pattern in HColumnDescriptor</link> changed method signatures so rather than return
            void they instead return HColumnDescriptor. This will throw</para>
        <screen>java.lang.NoSuchMethodError: org.apache.hadoop.hbase.HColumnDescriptor.setMaxVersions(I)V</screen>
        <para>.... so 0.92 and 0.94 are NOT compatible. You cannot do a rolling upgrade between them.</para> </section>
    <section
        xml:id="upgrade0.92">
        <title>Upgrading from 0.90.x to 0.92.x</title>
        <subtitle>Upgrade Guide</subtitle>
        <para>You will find that 0.92.0 runs a little differently to 0.90.x releases. Here are a few
            things to watch out for upgrading from 0.90.x to 0.92.0. </para>
        <note>
            <title>tl;dr</title>
            <para> If you've not patience, here are the important things to know upgrading. <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Once you upgrade, you can’t go back.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> MSLAB is on by default. Watch that heap usage if you have a lot of
                            regions.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> Distributed Log Splitting is on by default. It should make region server
                            failover faster. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> There’s a separate tarball for security. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> If -XX:MaxDirectMemorySize is set in your hbase-env.sh, it’s going to
                            enable the experimental off-heap cache (You may not want this). </para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </para>
        </note>

        <section>
            <title>You can’t go back! </title>
            <para>To move to 0.92.0, all you need to do is shutdown your cluster, replace your hbase
                0.90.x with hbase 0.92.0 binaries (be sure you clear out all 0.90.x instances) and
                restart (You cannot do a rolling restart from 0.90.x to 0.92.x -- you must restart).
                On startup, the <varname>.META.</varname> table content is rewritten removing the
                table schema from the <varname>info:regioninfo</varname> column. Also, any flushes
                done post first startup will write out data in the new 0.92.0 file format, <link
                    xlink:href="http://hbase.apache.org/book.html#hfilev2">HFile V2</link>. This
                means you cannot go back to 0.90.x once you’ve started HBase 0.92.0 over your HBase
                data directory. </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>MSLAB is ON by default </title>
            <para>In 0.92.0, the <link
                    xlink:href="http://hbase.apache.org/book.html#hbase.hregion.memstore.mslab.enabled">hbase.hregion.memstore.mslab.enabled</link>
                flag is set to true (See <xref
                    linkend="mslab" />). In 0.90.x it was <constant>false</constant>. When it is
                enabled, memstores will step allocate memory in MSLAB 2MB chunks even if the
                memstore has zero or just a few small elements. This is fine usually but if you had
                lots of regions per regionserver in a 0.90.x cluster (and MSLAB was off), you may
                find yourself OOME'ing on upgrade because the <code>thousands of regions * number of
                    column families * 2MB MSLAB (at a minimum)</code> puts your heap over the top.
                Set <varname>hbase.hregion.memstore.mslab.enabled</varname> to
                    <constant>false</constant> or set the MSLAB size down from 2MB by setting
                    <varname>hbase.hregion.memstore.mslab.chunksize</varname> to something less.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="dls">
            <title>Distributed Log Splitting is on by default </title>
            <para>Previous, WAL logs on crash were split by the Master alone. In 0.92.0, log
                splitting is done by the cluster (See See “HBASE-1364 [performance] Distributed
                splitting of regionserver commit logs” or see the blog post
                <link xlink:href="http://blog.cloudera.com/blog/2012/07/hbase-log-splitting/">Apache HBase Log Splitting</link>).
                This should cut down significantly on the
                amount of time it takes splitting logs and getting regions back online again.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Memory accounting is different now </title>
            <para>In 0.92.0, <xref
                    linkend="hfilev2" /> indices and bloom filters take up residence in the same LRU
                used caching blocks that come from the filesystem. In 0.90.x, the HFile v1 indices
                lived outside of the LRU so they took up space even if the index was on a ‘cold’
                file, one that wasn’t being actively used. With the indices now in the LRU, you may
                find you have less space for block caching. Adjust your block cache accordingly. See
                the <xref
                    linkend="block.cache" /> for more detail. The block size default size has been
                changed in 0.92.0 from 0.2 (20 percent of heap) to 0.25. </para>
        </section>


        <section>
            <title>On the Hadoop version to use </title>
            <para>Run 0.92.0 on Hadoop 1.0.x (or CDH3u3 when it ships). The performance benefits are
                worth making the move. Otherwise, our Hadoop prescription is as it has been; you
                need an Hadoop that supports a working sync. See <xref
                    linkend="hadoop" />. </para>

            <para>If running on Hadoop 1.0.x (or CDH3u3), enable local read. See <link
                    xlink:href="http://files.meetup.com/1350427/hug_ebay_jdcryans.pdf">Practical
                    Caching</link> presentation for ruminations on the performance benefits ‘going
                local’ (and for how to enable local reads). </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>HBase 0.92.0 ships with ZooKeeper 3.4.2 </title>
            <para>If you can, upgrade your zookeeper. If you can’t, 3.4.2 clients should work
                against 3.3.X ensembles (HBase makes use of 3.4.2 API). </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Online alter is off by default </title>
            <para>In 0.92.0, we’ve added an experimental online schema alter facility (See <xref
                    linkend="hbase.online.schema.update.enable" />). Its off by default. Enable it
                at your own risk. Online alter and splitting tables do not play well together so be
                sure your cluster quiescent using this feature (for now). </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>WebUI </title>
            <para>The webui has had a few additions made in 0.92.0. It now shows a list of the
                regions currently transitioning, recent compactions/flushes, and a process list of
                running processes (usually empty if all is well and requests are being handled
                promptly). Other additions including requests by region, a debugging servlet dump,
                etc. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Security tarball </title>
            <para>We now ship with two tarballs; secure and insecure HBase. Documentation on how to
                setup a secure HBase is on the way. </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Changes in HBase replication </title>
            <para>0.92.0 adds two new features: multi-slave and multi-master replication. The way to
                enable this is the same as adding a new peer, so in order to have multi-master you
                would just run add_peer for each cluster that acts as a master to the other slave
                clusters. Collisions are handled at the timestamp level which may or may not be what
                you want, this needs to be evaluated on a per use case basis. Replication is still
                experimental in 0.92 and is disabled by default, run it at your own risk. </para>
        </section>


        <section>
            <title>RegionServer now aborts if OOME </title>
            <para>If an OOME, we now have the JVM kill -9 the regionserver process so it goes down
                fast. Previous, a RegionServer might stick around after incurring an OOME limping
                along in some wounded state. To disable this facility, and recommend you leave it in
                place, you’d need to edit the bin/hbase file. Look for the addition of the
                -XX:OnOutOfMemoryError="kill -9 %p" arguments (See [HBASE-4769] - ‘Abort
                RegionServer Immediately on OOME’) </para>
        </section>


        <section>
            <title>HFile V2 and the “Bigger, Fewer” Tendency </title>
            <para>0.92.0 stores data in a new format, <xref
                    linkend="hfilev2" />. As HBase runs, it will move all your data from HFile v1 to
                HFile v2 format. This auto-migration will run in the background as flushes and
                compactions run. HFile V2 allows HBase run with larger regions/files. In fact, we
                encourage that all HBasers going forward tend toward Facebook axiom #1, run with
                larger, fewer regions. If you have lots of regions now -- more than 100s per host --
                you should look into setting your region size up after you move to 0.92.0 (In
                0.92.0, default size is now 1G, up from 256M), and then running online merge tool
                (See “HBASE-1621 merge tool should work on online cluster, but disabled table”).
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section
        xml:id="upgrade0.90">
        <title>Upgrading to HBase 0.90.x from 0.20.x or 0.89.x</title>
        <para>This version of 0.90.x HBase can be started on data written by HBase 0.20.x or HBase
            0.89.x. There is no need of a migration step. HBase 0.89.x and 0.90.x does write out the
            name of region directories differently -- it names them with a md5 hash of the region
            name rather than a jenkins hash -- so this means that once started, there is no going
            back to HBase 0.20.x. </para>
        <para> Be sure to remove the <filename>hbase-default.xml</filename> from your
                <filename>conf</filename> directory on upgrade. A 0.20.x version of this file will
            have sub-optimal configurations for 0.90.x HBase. The
                <filename>hbase-default.xml</filename> file is now bundled into the HBase jar and
            read from there. If you would like to review the content of this file, see it in the src
            tree at <filename>src/main/resources/hbase-default.xml</filename> or see <xref
                linkend="hbase_default_configurations" />. </para>
        <para> Finally, if upgrading from 0.20.x, check your <varname>.META.</varname> schema in the
            shell. In the past we would recommend that users run with a 16kb
                <varname>MEMSTORE_FLUSHSIZE</varname>. Run <code>hbase> scan '-ROOT-'</code> in the
            shell. This will output the current <varname>.META.</varname> schema. Check
                <varname>MEMSTORE_FLUSHSIZE</varname> size. Is it 16kb (16384)? If so, you will need
            to change this (The 'normal'/default value is 64MB (67108864)). Run the script
                <filename>bin/set_meta_memstore_size.rb</filename>. This will make the necessary
            edit to your <varname>.META.</varname> schema. Failure to run this change will make for
            a slow cluster. See <link
                        xlink:href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HBASE-3499">HBASE-3499
                        Users upgrading to 0.90.0 need to have their .META. table updated with the
                        right MEMSTORE_SIZE</link>
                </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
